<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The principall acts of foure Generall Assemblies, of the Kirk of Scotland holden [brace] at Edinburgh 1639, at Aberdene 1640, at S. Andrews and Edinburgh 1641, at S. Andrews 1642.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20345</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18959271</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205458</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240863578</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4233</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">18959271</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20345)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205458)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1665:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The principall acts of foure Generall Assemblies, of the Kirk of Scotland holden [brace] at Edinburgh 1639, at Aberdene 1640, at S. Andrews and Edinburgh 1641, at S. Andrews 1642.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 59, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect : print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205458:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205458:1"/>
            <p>THE PRINCIPALL ACTS <hi>OF</hi> FOURE GENERALL ASSEMBLIES, <hi>OF THE KIRK OF</hi> SCOTLAND: <hi>Holden</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>At EDINBURGH 1639.</item>
                  <item>At ABERDENE 1640.</item>
                  <item>At S. ANDREWS and EDINBURGH 1641.</item>
                  <item>At S. ANDREWS 1642.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>EDINBURGH: Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings most Excellent Majestie. <hi>Anno</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="edinburgh" type="assembly">
            <pb facs="tcp:205458:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205458:2"/>
            <head>THE GENERALL ASSEMBLY, At EDINBURGH 1639.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sess. VIII. <hi>August</hi> 17. 1639. <hi>Master</hi> George Grahame <hi>his renouncing and abjuring of Episcopacie.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The which day there was given in to the Assembly, direct from M.</hi> George Grahame, <hi>sometimes pretended Bishop of</hi> Orknay, <hi>an abjuration of Episce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, subscribed with his hand, which was publickly read in andience of the Assembly; and thereafter they ordained the same to be regestrat in the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Books</hi> ad perpetuam rei memoriam, <hi>whereof the tenor follows.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O all and sundry whom it effeirs, to whose knowledge these presents shall come, specially to the reverend and honourable Members of the future Assembly to be holden at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the twelfth day of <hi>August</hi> 1639. years: Me Master <hi>George Graham,</hi> sometime pretended Bishop of <hi>Orknay,</hi> being sorry and grieved at my heart that I should ever for any worldly respect have embraced the order of Episcopacie, the same having no warrant from the Word of God, and being such an order, as hath had sensibly many fearfull and evill consequences in many parts of Christendome, and particularly within the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as by dolefull and deplorable experience this day is manifest, to have disclaimed, like as I by the tenor hereof doe altogether disclaime and abjure all Episcopall power and jurisdiction, with the whole corruptions thereof, condemned by lawfull Assemblies within the said Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in regard the same is such an order as is also abjured with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the said Kirk, by vertue of that Nationall Oath which was made in the years 1580. and 1581. promising and swearing by the great Name of the Lord our God, That I shall never whiles I live, directly or indirectly, exerce any such power within the Kirk, neither yet shall I ever approve or allow the same, not so much as in my private or publike discourse: But on the contrary, shall stand and adhere to all the Acts and Constitutions of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205458:3"/>the late Assembly holden at <hi>Glasgow</hi> the 21. of <hi>Novem.</hi> 1638. last by-past, and shall concurre to the uttermost of my power, sincerely and faithfully, as occasion shall offer, in executing the said Acts, and in advancing the Work of Reformation within this Land, to the glory of God, the peace of the Country, and the comfort and contentment of all good Christians, as God shall be my help. In testimony of the which premisses, I have sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed thir presents with my hand at <hi>Breeknes</hi> in <hi>Stronnes,</hi> the eleventh day of <hi>February,</hi> the year of God 1639. years, before thir witnesses Master <hi>Walter Stuart,</hi> Minister at <hi>Southronnaldsay,</hi> Master <hi>James Heynd,</hi> Minister at <hi>Kirkwall,</hi> Master <hi>Robert Peirson,</hi> Minister at <hi>Firth,</hi> and Master <hi>Patrick Grahame,</hi> Minister at <hi>Holme,</hi> my son.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. VIII. 17. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1639. <hi>Act containing the Causes and Remedie of the by-gone evils of this Kirk.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kings Majestie having graciously declared, That it is His Royall will and pleasure, that all questions about Religion, and matters Ecclesiasticall be determined by Assemblies of the Kirk, having also by publike Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation indicted this free nationall Assembly, for set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling the present distraction of this Kirk, and for establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a perfect peace, against such divisions and disorders as have been sore displeasing to His Majestie, and grievous to all his good Subjects. And now His Majesties Commissioner <hi>John</hi> Earle of <hi>Traquair,</hi> intrusted and authorized with a full Commission, being present, &amp; sitting in this As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly, now fully conveened and orderly constitute in all the members thereof, according to the order of this Kirk, having at large declared His Majesties zeal to the reformed Religion, and His Royall care and tender affection to this Kirk, where his Majestie had both His Birth and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, His great displeasure at the manifold distractions and divisions of this Kirk and Kingdome, and His desires to have all our wounds perfectly cured with a fair and fatherly hand: And although in the way approven by this Kirk, tryall hath been taken in former Assemblies before from the Kirk registers, to our full satisfaction, yet the Commissioners Grace making particular enquiry from the members of the Assembly, now solemnely conveened, concerning the reall and true causes of so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great evills as this time past had so sore troubled the peace of this Kirk and Kingdome, It was represented to His Majesties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioner by this Assembly, That beside many other, the maine and most materiall causes were, First, The pressing of this Kirk, by the Prelates with a Service Book, or Book of Common Prayer, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out warrand or direction from the Kirk, and containing beside the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish frame thereof, divers Popish errors and ceremonies, and the seeds of manifold grosse Superstitions and Idolatry, with a Book of Canons, without warrand or direction from the Generall Assembly, establishing a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205458:3"/>tyrannicall power over the Kirk in the person of Bishops, and overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole discipline and government of the Kirk by Assemblies, with a Book of Consecration and Ordination, without warrand of Authoritie, Civill or Ecclesiasticall, appointing offices in the house of God, which are not warranted by the word of God, and repugnant to the discipline and Acts of our Kirk, and with the high Commission, erected without the consent of the Kirk, subverting the jurisdiction and ordinary Judicatories of this Kirk, and giving to persons meerely Ecclesiasticall, the power of both swords, and to persons meerly Civill, the power of the Keys and Kirk-sensures. A second cause was the Articles of <hi>Perth, viz.</hi> the obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Festivall dayes, kneeling at the Communion, Confirmation, Administration of the Sacraments in private places, which are brought in by a null Assembly and are contrary to the Confession of Faith, as it was meant and subscribed <hi>Anno</hi> 1580. and divers times since, and to the order and constitutions of this Kirk. Thirdly, the changing of the government of the Kirk, from the Assemblies of the Kirk to the persons of some Kirk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, usurping prioritie and power over their Brethren, by the way, and under the name of Episcopall government, against the Confession of Faith, 1580. against the order set downe in the Book of Policy, and against the intention &amp; constitution of this Kirk from the begining. Fourthly the Civill places and power of Kirk-men, their sitting in Session, Councell and Exchequer, their Riding, Sitting, and voting in Parliament, and their fitting in the Bench as Justices of peace, which according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions of this Kirk are incompatible with their spiritual sanction, lifting them up above their Brethren in worldly pomp, and do tend to the hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Ministrie. Fiftly the keeping &amp; authorizing corrupt Assemblies at <hi>Linlithgow,</hi> 1606. and 1608. At <hi>Glasgow,</hi> 1610. At <hi>Aberdene,</hi> 1616. At S. <hi>Andrews,</hi> 1617. At <hi>Perth,</hi> 1618. which are null and unlawfull, as being called and constitute quite contrary to the order and constitutions of this Kirk received and practised ever since the Reformation of Religion, and withal laboring to introduce novations into this Kirk, against the order and Religion established. A sixth cause is the want of lawfull and free Generall Assemblies, rightly constitute of Pastors, Doctors, and Elders yearly, or oftner <hi>prore nata,</hi> according to the libertie of this Kirk, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in the Book of Policy, and acknowledged in the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 1592. After which the whole Assembly in one heart and voyce did declare, that these and such other, proceeding from the neglect and breach of the Nationall Covenant of this Kirk and Kingdome, made in <hi>Anno</hi> 1580. have been indeed the true and maine causes of all our evills and distractions. And therefore ordain, according to the constituiions of the Generall Assemblies of this Kirk: and upon the grounds <hi>respective</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-specified, That the foresaid Service Book, Books of Cannons, and Ordination, and the high Commission, be still rejected; that the Articles of <hi>Perth,</hi> be no more practised: That Episcopall Government, and the Civill places and power of Kirk-men be holden still as unlawfull in this Kirk: That the above named pretended Assemblies, At <hi>Linlithgow</hi> 1606. and 1608. At <hi>Glasgow</hi> 1610. At <hi>Aberdene</hi> 1616. At S. <hi>Andrews</hi> 1617. At <hi>Perth</hi> 1618. be hereafter accounted as null, and of none effect. And that for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205458:4"/>preservation of Religion, and preventing all such evills in time-coming, Generall Assemblies rightly constitute, as the proper and competent judge of all matters Ecclesiasticall, heereafter be kept yearly and oftner, <hi>prore nata,</hi> as occasion and necessity shall require; The necessity of these oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casionall Assemblies being first remonstrate to His Majestie by humble snpplication: As also that Kirk Sessions, Presbyteries and Synodall As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies, be constitute and observed, according to the order of this Kirk.</p>
               <argument>
                  <p>After the voycing of the Act (anent the causes of our by gone evills) His Majesties Commissioner consented verbally to the said Act, and promised to give into the Clerk in writ, the Declaration of His consent, and that he should ratifie this Act in the ensuing Parliament.</p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. XVIII. 26. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1639. <hi>Act approving an old Register of the Generall Assembly.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The whole Assembly (upon the report made to them anent the old Register of the Assembly, gotten from Master</hi> John Rig) <hi>All in one voice approved the said Register, And ordained the same to make faith in judgement, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in all time coming, as a true and authentick Register of the Kirk of</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>conforme to the testimonie subscribed by the Committee, to be insert in the Books of Assembly: whereof the tenor followeth;</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E under-subscribers, Forsameikle as the late Generall Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly holden at <hi>Glasgow,</hi> gave power and Commission to us, To peruse, examine, and cognosce upon the validity, faith, and strength of the books and Registers of the Assembly, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly set down in the Commission given to us thereanent: According whereunto we did carefully view, peruse, and consider the saids Registers, and gave our testimony thereof under our hands, of the validity and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie of the samine, to the said Generall Assembly. And now having a new Commission given to us from the Generall Assembly now present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conveened and sitting at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> To peruse, examine, and cognosce upon the validity, faith and strength of another Register of the Assembly, which was not set down and recommended to us by the said former Commission, which Register beginneth at the Assembly holden at <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> the sixth day of <hi>March</hi> 1572. and endeth at the Assembly likewise holden at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 1573. we have carefully viewed, perused, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered the said Register: And being deeply and maturely advised, as in a matter of greatest weight and consequence, do attest before God, and upon our consciences declare to the world, and this present Assembly, That the said Register above exprest, is a famous, authentick, and good Register, which ought to be so reputed, and have publike faith in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205458:4"/>and outwith, as a valid and true Record in all things, And finds the same to be of the same hand-writ, and subscribed by the same Clerk of the Generall Assembly, as divers of the said other Registers (formeely perused by us) are. And in testimonie of our solemne affirmation we have subscribed these prefents with our hands, at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> day of <hi>August</hi> 1639.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act Sess. XIX. <hi>Aug.</hi> 27. 1639. <hi>Act approving the deposition of the Ministers by the Committees.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly, after the receiving of the whole reports from the Committees, appointed for revising of the processes and sentences, led, deduced, and pronounced before, and by the severall Commissions granted by the Assembly at <hi>Glasgow,</hi> All in one voice approved the saids whole processes as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly proceeded, and the whole sentences pronounced thereintill, as just and lawfull decrees, without prejudice of any favour that can be showne to any person or persons, against whom the said sentences are pronounced upon their supplications, or of Justice to such as complain of their processe, and offers to reduce the same upon whatsoever reason competent, by the Constitutions of this Kirk and Kingdome, before the Generall Assembly, and the Commissioners thereof, they being appointed for that effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act Sess. XX. 28. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1639. <hi>Act anent receiving of deposed Ministers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He which day the Generall Assembly upon the report of the Committees anent these who are deposed by Synods, Doe make this Generall Act, recommending to the Synods all these who are deposed before them for subscribing of the Declinator, and reading of the Service-Book and for no other grosse cause, That upon their true repentance and submission to the Constitutions of this Kirk, and upon their purgation and clearnesse from any grosse Faults laid to their charge in any new processe against them, they may be found by the Synods capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Ministrie, when God grants them an ordinary and lawfull call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by admission from the Presbyterie, either in the Church they served in before, or in any other Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:205458:5"/>
               <head>Act Sess. XXI. 29. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1639. <hi>Act anent the keeping of the Lords Day.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Generall Assembly recommendeth to the severall Presbyteries the execution of the old Acts of Assembly, against the breach of the Sabbath day, by going of Mylnes, Salt. Pannes, Salmond fishing, or any such like labour; and to this end revives and renues the Act of the Assembly holden at</hi> Haly-rudehouse, 1602. <hi>Sess.</hi> 5. <hi>whereof the tenor follows:</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly considering that the conventions of the People, specially on the Sabbath day are very rare in many places, by distraction of labour not only in harvest and seed-time, but also every Sabbath, by fishing both of white fish, and Salmond-fishing, and in going of Mylnes. Therefore the Assembly dischargeth and inhibiteth all such labour of fishing as well white fish as Salmond-fish, and going of Mylnes of all sorts upon the Sabbath, under the pain of incurring the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of the Kirk: And ordaines the Commissioners of this Assembly, to mean the same to His Majestie, and to desire that a pecuniall paine may be injoyned upon the contraveeners of this present Act.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act Sess. XXII. 29. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1639. <hi>à meridie. Articles and Overtures approved by the Assembly.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat some Commissioners be appointed to visit and peruse the whole Acts of Generall Assemblies, and to marke such Acts as are for the use of the Kirk in Generall, To extract the same out of the Registers, to the effect that after they be tryed, they may be printed according to the old Acts of the Assembly at <hi>Edinburgh March</hi> 7. 1574. <hi>Session</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Assembly appoints the Presbyterie of</hi> Edinburgh <hi>to have a care of this article, and to report their diligence to the next Assembly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That course may be taken for restraining of people from passing to <hi>England</hi> to marry, which is the occasion of great inconveniencies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Assembly alloweth this article, and recommends to the Parliament, that they would appoint a pecuniall snmme to be payed by the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veeners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Acts for furnishing expences to Commissioners, sent by the Presbyteries to the Generall Assembly, and sent in Commission by Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Assemblies, may be explained; And it be declared that all such Commissioners whatsoever, by their stipends may be furnished by the Kirks of the Presbyterie, according to the order set down in the Act of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205458:5"/>last Assembly, since the errand is common, and the benefit concerneth all: and that order may be taken, how that an expedient voluntarie course, thought fit by the Assembly, shall by advise of Parliament, have the force of a law, for compelling these to pay who are stented, both for the last and this Assembly, and in time to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Assembly allowes this article, and referres the same to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Session-Books of every Paroche be presented once a year to the Presbyteries, that they may be tryed by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Assembly alloweth this article.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Act of the 38. Assembly at <hi>Edinburgh, October</hi> 24. 1578. Sess. 8. ordaining Ministers who are deposed, to be charged under the pain of excommunication, to dimit their places, that they may be unquestionably vacand, may now be renewed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Assembly alloweth this article, and remits the same to the Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Assembly would revive or renew all former Acts of Assembly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Papists, and excommunicate persons, against haunters with them and receivers of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Assembly alloweth this article.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That an uniforme Catechisme may be appointed to be used through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this whole Kingdome in the examinations before the Communion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Assembly alloweth this article.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That all Ministers or Intrants presented to Kirks, be tryed before their admission, if they be qualified for the places to which they are presented, besides the ordinary tryalls of Expectants before their entrie to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Assembly alloweth this article.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. XXIII. 30. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1639. <hi>The Supplication of the Generall Assembly to the Kings Majesties Commissioner, concerning the Book, called,</hi> The large Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee the Members of this present Assembly, for our selves, and in name of the severall Presbyteries, Burghs, and Universities, for which we are Commissioners, resenting the great dishonour done to God, our King, this Kirk, and whole Kingdome, by the Book called, <hi>A large De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,</hi> have here represented the same to your Grace, and have collected some amongst many of false grosse &amp; absurd passages, That from the consideration therof, your Grace perceiving the intolerable evills foresaids contained therein, may be pleased to represent the same to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205458:6"/>our gracious Soveraigne, and in our behalfs humbly to beseech his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie, so much wronged by the many foul and false relations, suggested and perswaded to him as trueths, and by stealing the protection of His Royall Name and Authoritie to the patrocinie of such a Book: To be pleased first to call in the said Book, and thereby to shew his dislike there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Next to give Commission and warrant, To cite all such parties as are either knowne or suspect to have hand in it, and to appoint such as His Majestie knowes to be either authors, informers, or any wayes accessarie, being Natives of this Kingdome, To be sent hither to abide their tryall and censure before the Judge Ordinary, and in speciall Master <hi>Walter Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canquell,</hi> now Deane of <hi>Durham,</hi> who is known and hath professed to be the author, at least a vower and maintainer of a great part thereof; that by their examplar punishment, others may be deterred from such dangerous courses, as in such a way to raise sedition betwixt the King and His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, Gods honour may be vindicate from so high contempt, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties justice may appear, not only in cutting away such Malefactors, but in discouraging all such under-miners of His throne, His loyall and loving Subjects shall be infinitly contented to be cleared before the world of so false and unjust imputations, and will live hereafter in the greater securitie, when so dangerous a course of sedition is prevented, and so will have the greater and greater cause to pray for His Majesties long and prosperous Reigne.</p>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>His Majesties Commissioner in Councell having received the said supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, promised to impart the same to His Majesty, and to report his diligence therein.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>The Supplication of the Assembly to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties High Commissioner, and the Lords of secret Councell.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee the Generall Assembly, considering with all humble and thankfull acknowledgement, the many recent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours bestowed upon us by His Majestie, and that there resteth nothing for crowning of His Majesties incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable goodnesse towards us, but that all the members of this Kirk and Kingdom be joyned in one and the same Confession and Covenant with God, with the Kings Majestie, and amongst our selves: And conceiving the main lett and impediment to this so good a work, and so much wished by all, to have been the Informations made to His Majestie, of our Intentions to shake off civill and dutifull obedience due to Soveraignity, and to diminish the Kings greatnesse and authoritie, and being most willing and desirous to remove this and all such impediments which may hinder and impede so full and perfect an Union, and for clearing of our loyaltie, WEE in our own names, and in name of all the rest of the Subjects and Congregations whom we repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, do now in all humility represent to your Grace, His Majesties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioner,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205458:6"/>and the Lords of His Majesties most Honourable Privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and declares before God and the world, that we never had nor have any thought of with-drawing our selves from that humble and dutifull obedience to His Majestie, and to his government, which by the descent and under the reign of 107. Kings is most chearfully acknowledged by us and our predecessors: and that we never had, nor have any intention nor desire to attempt any thing that may tend to the dishonour of God, or the diminution of the Kings greatnesse and authoritie: But on the contrary, acknowledging our quietnesse, stabilitie and happinesse to depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the safety of the Kings Majesties Person, and maintenance of His greatnesse and royall authority who is Gods Vice-gerent set over us, for the maintenance of Religion and ministration of Justice, Wee have solemnly sworn and do sweare, not only our mutuall concurrence and assistance for the cause of Religion, and to the uttermost of our power, with our means and lives, to stand to the defence of our dread Soveraigne, his person and authority, in preservation and defence of the true Religion, Liberties and Lawes of this Kirk and Kingdome, but also in every cause which may concerne His Majesties honour, shall according to the Lawes of this Kingdome, and the dueties of good Subjects, concurre with our friends and followers in quiet manner, or in Armes, as we shall be required of His Majestie, His Councell, or any having his authority. And therefore being most desirous to cleare our selves of all imputation of this kinde, and following the laudable example of our predecessors, 1589. do most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly supplicate your Grace, His Majesties Commissioner, and the Lords of His Majesties most honourable Privie Councell, to enjoyn by Act of Councell, that this Confession and Covenant, which, as a testimony of our fidelity to God, and loyaltie to our King, we have subscribed, be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed by all His Majesties Subjects, of what rank and quality soever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>The Act of the Lords of Councell at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Aug. <hi>30. 1639.</hi> containing the Answer of the preceding Supplication.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He which day in presence of the Lord Commissioner and the Lords of Privie Councell, compeired personally <hi>John</hi> Earle of <hi>Rothes, James</hi> Earle of <hi>Montrose, John</hi> Lord <hi>Lowdoun,</hi> Sir <hi>George Stirling</hi> of Keir Knight, Sir <hi>William Douglas</hi> of Cavers Knight, Sir <hi>Henry Wood</hi> of Bonytoun Knight, <hi>John Smyth</hi> Burgesse of Edinburgh, Mr. <hi>Robert Barclay</hi> Provest of Irwing, Mr. <hi>Alexander Henderson</hi> Minister at Edinburgh, and Mr. <hi>Archbald Johnstoun</hi> Clerk to the Generall Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and in the name of the present sitting Generall Assembly, gave in to the Lord Commissioner and Lords of Privie Councell, the Petition above written; which being read, heard, and considered by the saids Lords, they have ordained, and ordain the same to be insert and registrate in the books
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205458:7"/>of Privie Councell, and according to the desire thereof, ordaines the said Confession and Covenant to be subscribed in time coming by all His Majesties Subjects of this Kingdome, of what ranke and quality so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <head>The Kings Majesties Commissioners Declarations.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He which day His Majesties Commissioner, and Lords of Councell, after the receiving of the Supplication of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Assembly, anent the subscribing of the Covenant, having returned to the Assembly, His Majesties Commissioner in name of the Councell, declared; that he had received the Supplication of the Assembly, desiring that the Covenant might receive the force of an Act of Councell, to be subscribed by all His Majesties Subjects, that they had found the desire so fair and reasonable, that they conceived themselves bound in duety to grant the same; and thereupon have made an Act of Councell to that effect: and that there rested now the Act of Assembly. And that he himself was so fully satisfied, that he came now as His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Commissioner to consent fully unto it: and that he was most willing that it should be enacted here in this Assembly, to oblige all His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Subjects to subscribe the said Covenant, with the Assemblies expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. And because there was a third thing desired, His subscription as the Kings Commissioner, unto the Covenant, which he behooved to do, with a Declaration in writ, and he declared as a Subject, he should sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe the Covenant as strictly as any, with the Assemblies Declaration; but as His Majesties Commissioner in his name behooved to prefix to his subscription, the Declaration following, which no <hi>Scots</hi> Subjects should subscribe, or have the benefit of, no not himself as Earle of <hi>Traquair.</hi> The tenor whereof follows:</p>
               <p>SEeing this Assembly, according to the laudable form and custome heretofore kept in the like cases, have in an humble and dutifull way, supplicate to us His Majesties Commissioner, and the Lords of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties most honourable Privie Councell, That the Covenant, with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of this Assembly, might be subscribed: And to that effect that all the Subjects of this Kingdome by Act of Councell be required to doe the same: And that therein for vindicating themselves from all suspitions of disloyaltie, or derogating from the greatnesse and authoritie of our dread Soveraigne, have therewith added a Clause, whereby this Covenant is declared one in substance with that which was subscribed by His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Father of blessed memory 1580, 1581, 1590. and oftner since renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Therefore I as His Majesties Commissioner, for the full satisfaction of the Subjects, and for settling a perfect Peace in Church and Kingdome, doe according to my foresaids Declaration and Subscription, subjoyned to the Act of this Assembly of the date the 17. of this instant, allow and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent that the Covenant be subscribed throughout all this Kingdome. In witnes whereof I have subscribed the premisses.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:205458:7"/>
               <head>Like as His Majesties Commissioner, read and gave in the Declaration following, of his consent to the Act of the Assembly <hi>17. August,</hi> anent the causes of our by-gone evils.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                  <hi>John</hi> Earle of <hi>Traquair,</hi> His Majesties Commissioner in this present Assembly, doe in His Majesties Name de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that notwithstanding of His Majesties own incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and many other grave and weightie considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet such is His Majesties incomparable goodnesse, that for settling the present distractions, and giving full satisfaction to the Subject, He doth allow, like as I His Majesties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioner do consent to the foresaid Act, &amp; have subscribed the premisses.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <head>Like as His Majesties Commissioner, read and gave in the Declaration following:</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is alwayes hereby declared by me His Majesties Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioner, That the practise of the premisses, prohibited within this Kirk and Kingdome, outwith the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> shall never bind nor inferre censure against the practises outwith the Kingdome: which when the Commissioner required to be insert in the Register of the Kirk, and the Moderator in name of the Assembly, refused to give warrant for such practise, as not agreeable with a good conscience, His Grace urged, that it should be recorded, at least that he made such a Declaration, whatsoever was the Assemblies Judgement in the contrair: And so it is to be understood to be insert here onely <hi>recitative.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act ordaining the subscription of the Confession of Faith and Covenant, with the Assemblies Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall Assembly considering the great happinesse which may flow from a full and perfect Union of this Kirk and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by joyning of all in one and the same Covenant with God, with the Kings Majestie, and amongst our selves, having by our great Oath declared the uprightnesse and loyaltie of our intentions in all our proceedings, and having withall supplicated His Majesties high Commissioner, &amp; the Lords of His Majesties honorable Privie Councell, to injoyn by Act of Councell, all the Lieges in time coming to subscribe the Confession of faith and Covenant, which as a testimogy of our fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to God and loyaltie to our King, we have subscribed; And seeing His Majesties high Commissioner, and the Lords of His Majesties honourable Privie Councell, have granted the desire of our Supplication, ordaining
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205458:8"/>by Civill authority, all His Majesties Lieges in time comming, to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe the foresaid Covenant, that our Union may bee the more full and perfect, We by our Act and Constitution Ecclesiasticall, do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proove the foresaid Covenant, in all the Heads and Clauses there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ordains of new, under all Ecclesiasticall censure, that all the Masters of Universities, Colledges, and Schooles, all Schollers at the passing of their degrees, all persons suspect of Papistry, or any other er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; and finally, all the members of this Kirk and Kingdome, subscribe the same with these words prefixed to their subscription: <hi>The Article of this Covenant, which was at the first subscription referred to the determination of the Generall Assembly, being determined. And thereby the five Articles of</hi> Perth, <hi>the government of the Kirk by Bishops, the civill places and power of Kirk men, upon the reasons and grounds contained in the Acts of the Generall Assembly declared to be unlawfull within this Kirk, we subscribe according to the determination foresaid.</hi> And ordains the Covenant, with this Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to be insert in the Registers of the Assemblies of this Kirk, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, Provinciall, and Presbyteriall, <hi>ad perpetuam rei memoriam;</hi> and in all humility supplicates His Majesties high Commissioner, and the honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Estates of Parliament, by their authority, to ratifie and injoyne the same under all civill paines, which will tend to the glory of God, preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> of Religion ,the Kings Majesties honour, and perfect peace of this Kirk and Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 30. 1639. <hi>Act anent Appellations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly appointed that in all time hereafter, no Appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons should be, leaping over either Presbyterie or Synod, but to ascend by degrees as from the Kirk Session to the Presbytry, or from the Presbyterie to the Synod, and from the Synod to the Generall Assembly, except it be after the Synod be past, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly before the Generall Assembly, or in the time thereof, and renews all former Acts made to this effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act anent advising with Synods and Presbyteries before determination in Novations.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall Assembly desiring that the intended Reformation being recovered, may be established, Ordains, that no Novati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which may disturbe the peace of the Church, and make divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, be suddenly proponed and enacted: But so as the motion be first communicate to the severall Synods, Presbyteries and Kirks, that the matter may be approved by all at home, and Commissioners may come well prepared, unanimously to conclude a solide deliberation upon these points in the Generall Assembly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:205458:8"/>
               <head>Act anent Ministers Catechising, and Family Exercises.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly considering that the long waited-for fruits of the Gospel, so mercifully planted and preserved in this Land, and the Reformation of our selves, and Families, so solemnly vowed to God of late in our Covenant, cannot take effect, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the knowledge &amp; worship of God be caried from the Pulpit to every family within each Parish, hath therefore appointed that every Minister, besides his paines on the Lords day, shall have weekly catechising of some part of the Paroch, and not altogether cast over the examination of the people, till a little before the Communion. Also that in every Familie the worship of God be erected, where it is not both Morning and Evening, and that the Children and Servants be catechised at home, by the Masters of the Families, whereof account shall be taken by the Minister, and Elders assisting him in the visitation of every Family: And lest they fail, that visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the severall Kirks be seriously followed by every Presbyterie, for this end among others. The execution and successe whereof, being tried by the Synods, let it be represented to the next Generall Assembly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. XXIIII. 30. <hi>Aug. à meridie. The Assemblies Supplication to the Kings Majestie.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Most Gracious Soveraigne,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee Your Majesties most humble and loyall Subjects, the Commissioners from all the parts of this your Majesties an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and Native Kingdome, and members of the Nationall Assembly, conveened at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by Your Majesties speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all indiction, and honoured with the presence of Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties high Commissioner, have been waiting for a day of rejoycing, and of solemne Thanksgiving to be rendred to God by this whole Kirk and Kingdome, for giving us a King so just and religious, that it is not only lawfull for us to be Christians under Your Majesties government, which sometime hath been the greatest praise of great Princes, but also that it hath pleased Your gracious Majestie, to make known that it is Your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all will and pleasure, that all matters Ecclesiasticall be determined in free Nationall Assemblies, and matters civill in Parliaments; which is a most noble and ample expression of Your Majesties justice, and we trust shall be a powerful mean of our common happinesse under your Majesties most blessed Reign. In the mean while we do most humbly, upon the knees of our hearts, blesse your Majesty for that happinesse already begun in the late Assembly at <hi>Edinburgh;</hi> in the proceedings whereof, next under God, we have laboured to approve our selves unto Your Majesties Vice-gerent, as if Your Majesties eyes had been upon us, which was the desire of our
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205458:9"/>souls, and would have beene the matter of our full rejoycing, and doe still continue Your Majesties most humble supplicants for Your Majesties ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill sanction and ratification of the constitutions of the Assembly in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; That your Majesties Princely power, and the Ecclesiasticall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority joyning in one, the mutuall embracements of religion and justice, of truth and peace may be seen in this Land, which shall be to us as a resurrection from the dead, and shall make us, being not only so farre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, but also revived, to fill Heaven and Earth with our praises, and to pray that King CHARLES may be more and more blessed, and His throne established before the Lord for ever.</p>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe Assembly appoints the next Generall Assembly, to sit at</hi> Aberdene <hi>the last Tuesday of</hi> July <hi>next,</hi> 1640. <hi>years. And warneth all Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, Universities and Burrows, to send their Commissioners, for keeping the samine. And thereafter the Assembly was concluded by giving of thanks by the Moderator, and singing of a Psalme, according to the custome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="aberdene" type="assembly">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:205458:9"/>
            <head>THE GENERALL ASSEMBLY, CONVEENED At ABERDENE <hi>July</hi> 28. 1640.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sess. II. 29. <hi>July</hi> 1640.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly having past the first day before they would make any Act in attending of His Majesties Commissioner.</p>
               <p>This day the Moderator openly asked in face of the Assembly, if there was any Commissioner come from His Majestie: And finding there was none, the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly proceeded according to their Liberties.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Overtures given in by the Committee appointed by the last Assembly, anent the ordering of the Assembly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house: Which being read in audience of the Assembly they approved the same.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly finds it expedient for the ordering of the House in all time coming, that the Commissioners sit together un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt, and that the places where they sit be railed about, or some other way divided from the seats of others, and that places be provided without the bounds of the Commission<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers seats to persons of respect, who are not Commissioners, and others according to their qualities, as the Magistrates of the Town shall find most convenient.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Also that the Commissioners, having received tickets from the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates of the Burgh, at the delivery of their Cōmissions, wherby they may have ready accesse to the Assemblie-House and place appointed for them, do keep the hour of meeting precisely, &amp; whosoever comes after the time, or shall be found absent at the calling of the Rols, to be censured as the Assemblie sees fitting: And whatsoever Presbyterie, Burgh or Universi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, shall not send Commissioners, or Commissioners sent from them doe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:205458:10"/>not come at all to the Assembly, be summond unto the next Assembly, and censured as the Assembly shall find reasonable.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> That foure persons of respect have warrant from the Assembly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne that there be no standing, no din, nor disorderly behaviour; And if any shall disobey them, or direct his speech to any, except to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator, and that one at once with leave first asked and given, to be rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked publikely by the Moderator: and if he desist not be removed out of the Assembly for that Session.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> That no motion come in unto the Assembly but by the Committee appointed for matters of that nature: and if the Committee refuse to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer the same, let it be proponed to the Assembly with the reasons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> That the minutes of ilk Session be read before their rising, and if the matter concerne the whole Kirk, let it be drawn up in forme and read in the begining of the next ensuing Session, that the Assembly may judge whether or not it bee according to their minde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act anent the demolishing of Idolatrous Monuments.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch as the Assembly is informed, that in divers places of this Kingdome, and specially in the North parts of the same, many Idolatrous Monuments, erected and made for Religious worship, are yet extant, Such as Crucifixes, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Christ, <hi>Mary,</hi> and Saints departed, ordaines the saids monuments to be taken down, demolished, and destroyed, and that with all convenient diligence: and that the care of this work shall be incumbent to the Presbyteries and Provinciall Assemblies within this Kingdome, and their Commissioners to report their diligence herein to the next Generall Assembly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act against Witches and Charmers.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly ordaines all Ministers within the Kingdome, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to take notice of Charmers, Witches, and all such abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers of the people, and to urge the Acts of Parliament, to be execute against them: And that the Commissioners from the Assembly to the Parliament, shall recommend to the said supreme judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory, the care of the execution of the Lawes against such persons in the most behoovefull way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:205458:10"/>
               <head>Sess. V. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1. 1640. <hi>Act for censuring speakers against the Covenant.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly ordaines, that such as have subscribed the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and speakes against the same, if he be a Minister, shall be deprived; and if he continue so, being deprived, shall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate: And if he be any other man, shall be dealt with as perjured, and satisfie publikely for his perjury.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. X. 5. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1640. <hi>Act against Expectants refusing to subscribe the Covenant.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly ordaines, that if any Expectant shall refuse to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe the Covenant, he shall be declared uncapable of a Peda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogie, teaching of a School, reading at a Kirk, Preaching with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Presbyterie, and shall not have libertie of residing within a Burgh, Universitie, or Colledge: And if they continue obstinate, to be processed.</p>
            </div>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Generall Assembly appoints the next Assembly, to be in</hi> S. Andrews <hi>the third Tuesday of</hi> July 1641. <hi>And that the Moderator in a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent way, by the secret Councell, or otherwise as may best serve, request the Kings Majestie to send his Commissioner to the said Assembly. And if any exigent fall out, that the Presbyterie of</hi> Edinburgh <hi>give advertisement for an Assembly</hi> pro re nata.</p>
            </argument>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="s. andrews and edinburgh" type="assembly">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:205458:11"/>
            <head>THE GENERALL ASSEMBLY, HOLDEN AT S. ANDREWS and EDINBURGH 1641.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Sess. I. 20. <hi>July</hi> 1641. Iohn <hi>Earle of</hi> VVeymes, <hi>His Majesties Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioner, presented His Majesties Letter to the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, whereof the tenor followeth.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <signed>CHARLES R.</signed>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Rustie and welbeloved, Wee greet you well. It is no small part of Our Royall care and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, that the true Reformed Religion, wherein by the grace of God, We resolve to live and dye, be settled peaceably in that Our ancient and native Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that the same be truly taught, and universally received and professed by Our Subjects there, of all degrees. For preventing of all division and trouble hereafter, We did intend in Our Own Royall Person, to have been present at this Assembly; but conceiving it to be unfitting, to detaine the Ministers from their particular charges, till the time of Our coming to the Parliament, We have resolved to make knowne unto you by these, and by Our Commissioner, That in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching Parliament, it is Our intention by Our authority, to ratifie and confirm the Constitutions of the late Assembly at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> that they may be obeyed by all Our Subjects living in that Our Kingdome. And that We will take into Our Royall consideration, by what meanes the Churches belonging to Our presentation, when any of them shall happen to vaik, may be best provided with well qualified Preachers: Like as We are not unwilling to grant presentations unto such as in these times of trouble have entred into the Ministerie, providing they have been examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Presbyteries, and approved by them: Because We want not Our own feares of the decay of Learning in that Church and Kingdome,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:205458:11"/>We intend also to consider of the best meanes for helping the Schooles and Colledges of Learning especially of Divinity, that there may be such a number of Preachers there, as that each Parish having a Minister, and the Gospel being preached in the most remote parts of the Kingdome, all Our Subjects may taste of Our care in that kinde, and have more and more cause to blesse God that we are set over them. And finally, so tender is Our care, that it shall not be Our fault if the Churches and Colledges there flourish not in Learning and Religion: For which Royall testimonie of Our goodnesse, We require nothing upon your part, but that which God hath bound you unto, even that you be faithfull in the charge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto you, and care for the soules of the people: That you study Peace and Unity amongst your selves, and amongst the people, against all Schisme and Faction; and that you not only pray for Us, but that you teach the People, which We trust are not unwilling to pay that honour and obedience which they owe unto Us, as his Vicegerent set over them, for their good; wherein We expect you will by your good example goe before them. Which hoping you will doe, We bid you farewell.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From Our Court at</hi> Whitehall, <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 10. <hi>day of July</hi> 1641.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. III. 28. <hi>July</hi> 1641. <hi>Act approving the Overtures of the Assembly at</hi> Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dene, <hi>for ordering the Assembly-House.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Overtures for ordering the Assembly-House, given in to, and approved by the Assembly of <hi>Aberdene</hi> the 29. <hi>July</hi> 1640. Act Sess. 2. were openly read, and again approved by this Assembly, and ordained to be kept the whole time thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. V. 30. <hi>July</hi> 1641. <hi>Act anent old Ministers bruiking their Benefices.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly having considered the Supplication given in by Doctor <hi>Robert Howie,</hi> Provest of the New Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of S. <hi>Andrews,</hi> whereby he craved, that (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of his dismission of his charge) he should not be prejudged of his full provision and maintenance du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his life time: The Assembly thinks it fit and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, that his provision and maintenance should not be diminished, but that he should injoy the same fully, as of before, during all the dayes of his life-time, and craveth his dismission to be only but a cessation from his charge, because of his age and inability: And declares, that old Ministers and professors of Divinitie, shall not by their cessation
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205458:12"/>from their charge, through age and inabilitie, be put from injoying their old maintenance and dignity. And recommends this and others the like things, concerning the estate of that Universitie of S. <hi>Andrews,</hi> to the Parliament, and the Visitation to be appointed from the Assembly and Parliament. And likewise the Assembly being informed, that the said Doctor <hi>Howie</hi> hath been very painfull in his charge, and that he hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers papers which would be very profitable for the Kirk: Therefore they think fit, that the said doctor <hi>Howie</hi> be desired to collect these papers, which doeth concerne, and may be profitable for the use of the Kirk, that the samine may be showne to the Visitors of the said Universitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. VIII. 2. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1641. <hi>à meridie. Act against sudden receiving Ministers deposed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly ordaines, that Ministers who are deposed either by Presbyteries, Synods, or Generall Assemblies, or Committees from Assemblies for the publike cause of the Reformation and order of this Kirk, shall not be suddenly received againe to the Ministerie, till they first evidence their repentance both before the Presbyterie and Synod, within the bounds where they were deposed, and thereafter the samine reported to the next ensuing Generall Assembly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="overtures">
               <head>Sess. IX. <hi>Aug.</hi> 3. 1641.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Overtures under-written, concerning the Uniuersities and Colledges of this Kingdome, to be represented by the Generall Assembly, to the Kings Majesty and Parliament, being openly read, the Assembly approved the saids Overtures, and ordained them to be recommended to the Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irst, because the good estate both of the Kirk and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, dependeth mainly upon the flourishing of Universities and Colledges, as the Seminaries of both, which cannot be expected, unlesse the poore meanes which they have, be helped, and sufficient revenues be provided for them and the same well imployed: Therefore that out of the rents of Prelacies, Collegiat or Chapter-Kirks, or such like, a sufficient maintenance be provided for a competent number of Professors, Teachers, and Bursers in all faculties, and especially in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie, and for upholding, repairing, and enlarging the Fabrick of the Colledges, furnishing Libraries, and suchlike good uses in every Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie and Colledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Next for keeping of good order, preveening and removing of abuses, and promoving of pietie and learning, it is very needfull and expedient, that there be a communion and correspondencie kept betwixt all the Universities and Colledges. And therefore that it be ordained, that there
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205458:12"/>be a meeting once every year at such times and places as shall be agreed upon, of Commissioners from every University and Colledge to consult and determine upon the common affairs, and whatsoever may concerne them, for the ends above-specified, and who also, or some of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber may represent what shall be needfull and expedient for the same effect, to Parliaments and Generall Assemblies.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> that speciall care be had that the places of the Professors, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of Professors of Divinity in every University and Colledge, Be filled with the ablest men, and best affected to the Reformation and order of this Kirk.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. X. <hi>Aug.</hi> 4. 1641. <hi>Act against Impiety and Schisme.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly seriously considering the present case and condition of this Kirk &amp; Kingdom, what great things the Lord hath done for us, especially since the renewing of our Covenant, notwithstanding our former backsliding and desertion; and if we shall either become remisse in the dueties of Piety, or shall not constantly hold &amp; keep our Religion, unto which we have bound our selves so straitly &amp; solemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what dishonour we doe unto the name of God before men, who have their eyes upon us, and how great judgements we bring upon our selves, upon these and the like considerations, The Assembly doth finde it most necessary to stirre up themselves, and to provoke all others both Ministers and people of all degrees, not only to the religious exercises of publike worship in the Congregation, and of private worship in their Families, and of every one by themselves apart, but also to the dueties of mutuall edification, by instruction, admonition, exhorting one another to forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in Religion, and comforting one another in whatsoever distresse; and that in all their meetings, whither in the way of civill conversation, or by reason of their particular callings, or any other occasion offered by divine providence, no corrupt communication proceed out of their mouth, but that which is good to the use of edifying, that it may minister grace unto the hearers: And because the best means have been, and may still be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised or abused, and particularly the duetie of mutuall edification, which hath been so little in use, and so few know how to practise in the right manner, may be upon the one part subject to the mocking of ungodly and worldly men, who cannot endure that in others, which they are not willing to practise themselves, and upon the other part, to many errors and abuses, to which the godly through their weaknes may fall, or by the craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinesse of others may be drawn into, such as are Error, Heresie, Schisme, Scandall, Self-conceit, and despising of others, pressing above the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon calling of Christians, &amp; usurping that which is proper to the Pastoral Vocation, contempt or misregard of the publike means, idle and unprofit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:205458:13"/>questions which edifie not, uncharitable censurings, neglect of duties in particular callings, businesse in other mens Matters and Callings, and many such others in doctrine, charity, and manners, which have dolefully rent the bowels of other Kirks, to the great prejudice of the Gospel.</p>
               <p>Therefore the Assembly, moved with the zeal of God against all abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and corruptions, and according to their manifold obligations, most earnestly desiring and thirsting to promove the work of Reformation, and to have the comfort &amp; power of true godlinesse, sensible to every soul, and Religion to be universally practised in every Family, and by every person at all occasions, Doth charge all the Ministers and Members of this Kirk whom they doe represent, that according to their severall places and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, they endeavour to suppresse all impiety and mocking of religious exercises, especially of such as put foule aspersions, and factious or odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous names upon the godly. And upon the other part, that in the fear of God they be aware and spiritually wise, that under the name and pretext of religious exercises, otherwayes lawfull and necessary, they fall not into the aforesaid abuses; especially, that they eschew all meetings which are apt to breed Error, Scandall, Schisme, neglect of dueties and particular callings, and such other evills as are the works, not of the spirit, but of the flesh, and are contrary to truth and peace; and that the Presbyteries and Synods have a care to take order with such as transgresse the one way or the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. XIIII. 6. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1641. <hi>à meridie. Act anent Novations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince it hath pleased God to vouchsafe us the libertie of yearly Generall Assemblies, It is ordained according to the Acts of the Assembly at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 1639. and at <hi>Aberdene,</hi> 1640. that no Novation in doctrine, worship, or government, be brought in, or practised in this Kirk, unlesse it be first propounded, examined, and allowed in the Generall Assembly, and that transgressors in this kinde be censured by Presbyteries and Synods.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act Sess. XV. 7. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1641. <hi>Overtures anent Bursars, and Expectants.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Overtures under-written being openly read in audience of the Assembly, were approved, and declared by them to be Acts of the Assembly, in all time coming, to be observed</hi> respective, <hi>as the samine bears.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly thinks meet for maintaining of Bursars of Divinitie, that every Presbyterie that consists of twelve Ministers, shall maintain a Bursar, and where the number is fewer nor twelve, shall be joyned with these out of another Presbyterie where their number ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:205458:13"/>where this course is not already kept, it is to be begun without lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger delay, and every Provinciall is ordained to give an accompt of their number of Bursars, that is constantly to be entertained by their Province, at the next ensuing Generall Assembly.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> No Expectant shall be permitted to preach in publike before a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, till first he be tryed after the same manner, how beit not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with that accuracie which is injoyned by the Act of the Assembly of <hi>Glasgow</hi> 1638. which prescribes the order and manner of tryall, that is to be kept with these who are to be admitted to the holy Ministrie: and none so tryed shall preach in publike, without the bounds of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity or Presbyterie where he past his tryalls, till he first make it known to the other Presbyteries, where he desires to be heard, by a testimoniall from the Universitie or Presbyterie where he lived, that he hath bin of an honest conversation, and past his tryalls conform to the order here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed: Which being done in the meeting of the Province or Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, where he desires to be heard; he is to be allowed by them to preach within the bounds of that Province or Presbyterie, without any further tryall to be taken of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Expectants being educate in a Colledge that was corrupt, or under a corrupt Minister, if they themselves have been known to have been tainted with error, or opposite to our Covenant, and the blessed Work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation within this Kirk, the same order is to be kept in admitting them to the holy Ministrie, or to any place in the Colledges or Schooles of this Kingdome, that was ordained to be kept in admission of these Ministers who fled out of the Countrey, and shew themselves opposite to our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Reformation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act Sess. XVII. <hi>Aug.</hi> 9. 1641. <hi>Act against unlawfull Bands.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly taking to their consideration the question proponed unto them concerning the Band, the copy whereof was present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before them from the Parliament, doth find and declare that Bands of this and the like nature, may not lawfully be made: By which Declaration the Assembly doth not intend to bring any censure for what is past, and by the wisedome and care of the Committee of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is taken away, upon any person, who being required by the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator and the Clerk, shall under his hand declare before them, That as the Assembly doth finde that the subscribers are not astricted by their Oath to the tenor of the said Band, so he findeth himself not to be astrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Oath to the tenor thereof; but the intention of the Assembly is meerly to prevent the like in time coming.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:205458:14"/>
               <head>Sess. XVIII. 9. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1641. <hi>à meridie. A Letter from some Ministers in</hi> England <hi>to the Assemblie.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Reverend and dear Brethren, now conveened in this Generall Assembly.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee most heartily salute you in the Lord, rejoycing with you in his unspeakable goodnesse, so miraculously pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering your late endeavours, both for the restoring and settling of your own Liberties and Priviledges, in Church and common wealth (which we heare and hope he is now about to accomplish) as also for the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioning and advancing of the Worke of Reformation among our selves; for which as we daily blesse the highest Lord, sole Author of all our good, so doe we acknowledge your selves worthy Instruments thereof. And for that (besides all other respects) doe, and ever shall (by the help of God) hold you deare unto us, as our own bowels, and our selves obliged to render unto you all due correspondence according to our power, upon all good occasions.</p>
               <p>And now (deare Brethren) forasmuch as the Church of Christ is but one body, each part whereof cannot but partake in the weale and woe of the whole, and of each other part; and these Churches of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> may seem both to be imbarqued in the same bottome, to sink and swim together, and are so near conjoyned by many strong tyes, not only as fellow-members under the same Head Christ, and felow-subjects under the same King; but also by such neighbour-hood and vicinity of place, that if any evill shall much infest the one, the other cannot bee altogether free: or if for the present it should, yet in processe of time it would sensibly suffer also. And forasmuch as evills are better remedied in their first begining, then after they have once taken deep root; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we whose names are here under-written, in the behalf of our selves, and of many others, Ministers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are bold to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to your consideration (being met together in this venerable Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) a difference of great concernment, which you may please (in brief) thus to understand. Almighty God having now of his infinite goodnesse raised up our hopes of removing the yoke of Episcopacie (under which we have so long groaned) sundry other forms of Church-government are by sundry sorts of men projected, to be set up in the roome thereof: one of which (amongst others) is of some Brethren that hold the whole power of Church-government, and all Acts thereunto appertaining (as Election, Ordination, and Deposition of Officers, with Admission, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, and Absolution of Members) are by divine Ordinance <hi>in foro externo,</hi> to be decreed by the most voyces, in, and of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation, which (say they) is the utmost bound of a particular Church, endued with power of government, and only some Formalities
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205458:14"/>of solemne execution to be reserved to the Officers (as servants of the saids Church) if they have any, or if none, then to be performed by some other members, not in office, whom the said Church shall appoint there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: And that every of the said particular Congregations (whether they consist of few or many members, and be furnished with Officers or not) lawfully may and ought to transact, determine and execute all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters pertaining to the government of themselves, amongst and within themselves without any authoritative (though not consulatory) concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or interposition of any other persons or Churches whatsoever, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning all imperative and decisive power of Classes, or compound Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries and Synods, as a meere usurpation. Now because we conceive that your judgement in this case may conduce much by the blessing of God, to the settling of this question amongst us; Therefore we doe earnestly intreat the same at your hands, and that so much the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we sometimes hear from those of the aforesaid judgment, that some famous and eminent Brethren, even amongst your selves, doe somewhat encline unto an approbation of that way of government. Thus humbly craving pardon for our boldnesse, leaving the matter to your grave con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations, and expecting answer at your convenient leasure, We commit you, and the successe of this your meeting, to the blessing of the Almighty, in whom we shall ever remain,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>London,</hi>
                     <date>12. <hi>July.</hi> 1641.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your faithfull Brethren to serve you in all offices of love.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Assemblies Answer to the English Ministers Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right reverend and dearly beloved Brethren in our Lord and common Saviour Jesus Christ.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee the Ministers and Elders met together in this Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Assembly, were not a little refreshed and comforted by the good report which we heard of you, and others of our Brethren of the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> by some of our Ministers, who by the good providence of our Lord had seen your faces, and conversed with you. But now yet more comforted by your Letters which we received, and which were read in the face of the Assembly, witnessing your Christian love, and rejoycing with us in God for his great and wonderfull Work in the Reformation of this Kirk, and in the beginning of a blessed Reformation amongst your selves, and that you are so sensible of your communion and fellowship with us, and to desire to know our minde and judgement of that which some Brethren amongst you hold, concerning Kirk-government.</p>
               <p>We doe with our hearts acknowledge and wonder at the great and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable wisedome, mercie, and power of our God, in restoring unto us the truth and puritie of Religion, after many Back slidings and defection of some in this Kirk, and desire not only to confesse the same before the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:205458:15"/>world, and all other Christian Kirkes, but also doe pray for grace to walk worthy of so wonderfull a love: We have been helped by your prayers, in our weak endeavours, and you have mourned with us, (we know) in the dayes of our mourning; and therefore is it that you doe now rejoyce and praise God with us: Neither are we out of hope, but the same God shall speedily perfect that which he hath begun amongst you, that your joy may be full: which is the desire of our soule, and for which we doe now pray, and in our severall Congregations will be instant at the throne of grace, for this and all other spirituall and temporall blessings upon the Kirk and Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> by name, expecting the like performance of mutuall love from you, and others equally minded with you, for your parts, till a common consent may be obtained, even that you will recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> by name in your prayers to God. Thus shall we be as one people, mourning and rejoycing, praying and praising to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; which may be one meane of the preservation of Unity, and of many other blessings to us both.</p>
               <p>We have learned by long experience, ever since the time of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and specially after the two Kingdomes have been (in the great goodnesse of God to both) united under one Head and Monarch, but most of all of late, which is not unknown to you, what danger and conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in matters of Kirk-government, of divine worship, and of doctrine, may come from the one Kirk to the other, which beside all other reasons, make us to pray to God, and to desire you, and all that love the honour of Christ, and the peace of these Kirks and Kingdomes, heartily to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that there might be in both Kirks, one Confession, one Directory for publike worship, one Catechisme, and one Forme of Kirk-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And if the Lord who hath done great things for us, shall be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to hearken unto our desires, and to accept of our endeavours, we shall not only have a sure foundation for a durable Peace, but shall be strong in God, against the rising or spreading of Heresie and Schisme amongst our selves, and of invasion from forraine enemies.</p>
               <p>Concerning the different Formes of Kirk-government, projected by sundrie sorts of men, to be set up in place of Episcopall Hierarchie, which we trust is brought near unto its period, we must confesse, that we are not a little grieved that any godly Ministers and Brethren should be found, who doe not agree with other Reformed Kirks in the point of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as well as in the matter of Doctrine and worship; and that we want not our own feares, that where the hedge of Discipline and Governmens is different, the Doctrine and Worship shall not long continue the same without change: yet doe not marvell much, that particular Kirks and Congregations which live in such places, as that they can conveniently have no dependencie upon superiour Assemblies, should stand for a kind of independencie and supremacie in themselves, they not considering that in a Nation or Kingdome, professing the same Religion, the government of the Kirk by compound Presbyteries and Synods is a help and strength, and not a hinderance or prejudice to particular Congregations and Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, in all the parts of Kirk government; and that Presbyteries and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods are not an extrinsecall power set over particular Kirks, like unto Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:205458:15"/>dominion, they being no more to be reputed extrinsecall unto the particular Kirks, nor the power of a Parliament, or Convention of Estates, where the Shires and Cities have their own Delegates, is to be held ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinsecall to any particular Shire or City.</p>
               <p>Our unanimous judgement and uniforme practice, is, that according to the order of the Reformed Kirks, and the ordinance of God in his Word, not onely the solemne execution of Ecclesiasticall power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, but the whole acts and exercise thereof, do properly belong unto the Officers of the Kirk; yet so that in matters of chiefest importance, the tacite consent of the Congregation be had, before their decrees and sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences receive finall execution, and that the Officers of a particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, may not exercise this power independently, but with subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation unto greater Presbyteries and Synods, Provinciall and Nationall: which as they are representative of the particular Kirks conjoyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one under their government; so their determination, when they proceed orderly, whether in causes common to all, or many of the Kirks, or in causes brought before them by appellations or references from the inferiour, in the case of aberation of the inferiour, is to the severall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations authoritative and obligatorie and not consultatory only: And this dependencie and subordination, we conceive not only to be warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the light of nature, which doth direct the Kirk in such things as are common to other societies, or to be a prudentiall way for Reformation, and for the preservation of Truth and Peace, against Schisme, Heresie, and Tyranny, which is the sweet fruits of this government wheresoever it hath place, and which we have found in ancient and late experience; but also to be grounded upon the word of God, and to be conforme to the paterne of the Primitive and Apostolicall Kirks: and without which, neither could the Kirks in this Kingdome have been reformed, nor were we able for any time to preserve Truth and Unity amongst us.</p>
               <p>In this forme of Kirk-government, our unanimity and harmony by the mercy of God, is so full and perfect, that all the Members of this Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have declared themselves to be of one heart, and of one soule, and to be no lesse perswaded, that it is of God, then that Episcopall government is of men; resolving by the grace of God, to hold the same constantly all the dayes of our life, and heartily wishing that God would blesse all the Christian Kirks, especially the famous Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> unto which in all other respects we are so nearly joyned with this divine Forme of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thus having briefly and plainly given our judgement for your satif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and desiring and hoping that ye will beleeve against all mis-reports, that we know not so much as one man, more or lesse eminent amongst us, of a different judgement, we commend you unto the riches of the grace of Christ, who will perfect that which he hath begun amongst you, to your unspeakable comfort. Subscribed by our Moderator and Clerk.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Edinburgh</hi>
                     <date>9. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1641.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:205458:16"/>
               <head>The Assemblies Answer to the Kings Majesties Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Most gracious Soveraign,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eside the conscience of that duetie which we owe to supreme Authority, we are not only encouraged, but confirmed by the Royall favour and Princely munificence, expressed in Your gracious Majesties Letters, which filled our hearts with joy, and our mouths with praise, to offer up our prayers with the greater fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vencie to God Almightie for Your Majesties happinesse, our selves for our own parts, and for the whole Kirks of this your Majesties Kingdome, which we doe represent, to serve Your Majestie in all humble obedience, our faithfull labours for preserving Trueth and Peace amongst all Your Majesties Subjects, and our example (according to Your Majesties just commandments laid upon us) to be a presedent to others in paying that honour,) which by all Lawes divine and humane, is due unto Your sacred Majestie, being confident that your Majestie shall finde at your coming hither much more satisfaction and content then can be expressed by</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Your Majesties most humble Subjects and faithfull servants, the Ministers and Elders met together in the venerable Assembly at</hi> S. Andrews, <date>
                        <hi>July</hi> 20.</date>
                     <hi>and</hi> Edinburgh, <date>
                        <hi>July</hi> 27. 1641.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act anent the Kirk of <hi>Campheir.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He which day a motion was made in the Assembly, that it seemed expedient for correspondencie that might be had from forraigne parts, for the weal of this Kirk, That the Scots Kirk at <hi>Campheir</hi> were joyned to the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as a Member thereof: Which being seriously thought upon and considered by the Assembly, they approved the motion, and ordained M. <hi>Robert Baillie</hi> Minister at <hi>Cilwinning,</hi> to write to M. <hi>William Spang</hi> Minister at <hi>Campheir,</hi> and Kirk Session thereof, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to send their Minister, and a ruling Elder, instructed with a Commission to the next Generall Assembly to be holden at S. <hi>Andrews,</hi> the last Wednesday of <hi>July</hi> 1642. at which time they should be inrolled in the Books of the Generall Assembly, as Commissioners of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Assembly of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from the Scots Kirk at <hi>Campheir.</hi>
               </p>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe Assembly appoints the next Generall Assembly to be holden at</hi> S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews, <hi>the last Wednesday of July next</hi> 1642.</p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="s. andrews" type="assembly">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:205458:16"/>
            <head>THE GENERALL ASSEMBLY, CONVEENED At S. ANDREWS <hi>July</hi> 27. 1642.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Act Sess. I. 27. <hi>July</hi> 1642. <hi>The Kings Letter to the Generall Assembly, presented by His Majesties Commissioner, the Earle of</hi> Dumfermling, <hi>July</hi> 27. 1642.</head>
               <opener>
                  <signed>CHARLES R.</signed>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the midst of Our great and weighty affaires of Our other kingdoms, which God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who is privie to Our Intentions, and in whom We trust, will in his own time bring to a wished and peaceable conclusion, We are not unmindfull of that duetie which we owe to that Our ancient and native Kingdome, and to the Kirks there, now met together by their Commissioners in a Nationall Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. God whose Vicegerent We are, hath made Us a King over divers Kingdomes, and We have no other desire, nor designe, but to govern them by their own Lawes, and the Kirks in them by their own Canons and Constitutions. Where any thing is found to be amisse, We will endeavour a Reformation in a fair and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way; and where a Reformation is settled, We resolve, with that autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie wherewith God hath vested Us, to maintain and defend it in peace and libertie, against all trouble that can come from without, and against all Heresies, Sects and Schismes which may arise from within, Nor do We desire any thing more in that Kingdom (and when We shall hear of it, it shall be a delight and matter of gladnesse unto Us) then that the Gospel be faithfully preached throughout the whole Kingdom, to the outmost skirts
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:205458:17"/>and borders thereof. Knowing that to be the mean of honour to God, of happinesse to the people, and of true obedience to Us. And for this effect, that holy and able men be put in places of the Ministery, and that Schooles and Colledges may flourish in Learning and true Pietie. Some things for advancing of those ends, We did of Our own accord promise in Our Letters to the last Assembly, and We make your selves Judges, who were witnesses to Our Actions, while We were there in Person, whether we did not perform them both in the point of presentations which are in our hands, and in the liberall provision of all the Universities and Colledges of the Kingdome, not only above that which any of Our Progenitors had done before Us; but also above your owne hopes and expectation. We doe not make commemoration of this Our Beneficence, either to please Our selves, or to stop the influence of Our Royall good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and bountie for afterward, but that by these reall demonstrations of Our unfained desires and delight to do good, you may be the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident to expect from Us, whatsoever in Justice We can grant, or what may be expedient for you to obtaine. We have given expresse charge to Our Commissioner, to fee that all things be done there orderly and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, as if We were present in Our Own Person; not doubting but in thankfulnesse for your present estate and condition, you will abstaine from every thing that may make any new disturbance, and that you will be more wile then to be the enemies of your own peace, which would but stumble others, and ruine your selves. We have also commanded Our Commissioner to receive from you your just and reasonable desires, for what may further serve for the good of Religion, that taking them to Our consideration, We may omit nothing which may witnesse Us to be indeed a nursing Father of that Kirk, wherein We were born and baptized, and that if ye be not happy, you may blame not Us, but your selves. And now what doe We again require of you, but that which otherwise you owe to Us as your Soveraigne Lord and King, even that ye pray for Our prosperitie and the peace of Our Kingdomes, that ye use the best meanes to keep Our People in obedience to Us and Our Lawes, which doth very much in Our personall absence from that Our Kingdome depend upon your preaching, and your owne examplary loyaltie and faithfulnesse, and that against all such jealousies, suspitions and sinister rumors as are too frequent in these times, and have been often falsified in time past, by the reality of the contrary events: Ye judge Us and Our professions by Our actions, which We trust through God in despight of malice shall ever go on in a constant way for the good of Religion, and the weal of Our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which is the Chiefest of Our intentions and desires. And thus We bid you farewell.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Given at Our Court at</hi> Leicester, <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 23. <hi>of</hi> July, 1642.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>To Our trusty and wel beloved the Generall Assembly in Our Kingdom of</hi> Scotland <hi>convcened at S.</hi> Andrews.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:205458:17"/>
               <head>Act Sess. III. <hi>July</hi> 29. 1642. <hi>Act for bringing in of the Synode Books yeerly to the Generall Assemblies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Moderator calling to minde that which was forgotten in the preceeding Sessions, the examination of the Provinciall Books, caused call the Roll of the Provinciall Assemblies, And the Assembly finding very few Provinces to have sent their Books to this Assembly, notwithstanding of the ordinance of the former Assembly thereanent, for the more exact obedience of that ordinance hereafter, the Assembly in one voyce ordaines, That the Books of every Provinciall Assembly shall be brought and produced to every Generall Assembly: And that this may be performed, ordaines that every Clerk of the Provincialls, either bring or send the said Books yearly to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Assemblies, by the Commissioners sent to the Assemblies, from these Presbyteries where the Clerks reside. Which charge the Assembly also layes upon the said Commissioners, sent from the saids Presbyteries where the Clerks reside, ay and while some meanes be provided, whereby the Clerks charges may be sustained for coming with the saids Books themselves: And that under the pain of deprivation of the Clerk in case of his neglect, and of such censure of the saids commissioners, in case of their neglect as the Assembly shall think convenient.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act Sess. V. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1. 1642. <hi>Act anent the choosing of Kirk Sessions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nent the question moved to the Assembly, concerning the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Kirk Sessions, The Assembly ordaines the old Session to elect the new Session both in Burgh and Land. And that if any place shall vaik in the Session chosen, by death or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, the present Session shall have the election of the person to fill the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cand roome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>Sess. VI. 2. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642. <hi>The report of the interpretation of the Act at</hi> Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, <hi>anent tryall of Ministers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He meaning of the foresaid Act, is not that an actuall Minister to be transported, shal be tried again by the tryals appointed for try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Expectants, at their entry to the Ministery, according to the Acts of the Kirk; but only that he bringing a Testimoniall of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer tryalls, and of his abilities, and conversation, from the Presbyterie
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:205458:18"/>from whence he comes, and giving such satisfaction to the Parochiners Presbyterie whereto he comes in preaching, as the Presbyterie finds his gifts fit and answerable for the condition and disposition of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, whereto he is presented. Because, according to the Act of the Assembly 1596. renewed at <hi>Glasgow,</hi> some that are meet for the Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in some places, are not meet for all alike: and Universities, Towns and Burghs, and places of Noblemens residence, or frequencie of Papists, and other great and eminent Congregations, and in sundry other cases, require men of greater abilities, nor will be required necessarily in the planting of all private small Paroches, the leaving of the consideration of these cases unto the judgement and consideration of the Presbyterie, was the only intention of the Act.</p>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Assembly approves the meaning and interpretation foresaid: and appoints the said Act, according to this interpretation, to stand in force, and to have the strength of an Act and Ordinance of Assembly in all time coming.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act Sess. VII. 3. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642. <hi>Act anent the order for making Lists to His Majestie, and other Patrons for Presentations; the order of tryal of Expectants, and for trying the quality of Kirks.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orsameikle as His Majestie was graciously pleased in His Answer to the Petition, tendred by the Commissioners of the late Assembly to His Majestie, to declare and promise, for the better providing of vaiking Kirks at His Majesties Presentation with qualified Ministers, to present one out of a list of six persons, sent to His Majestie from the Presbyteries wherein the vaiking Kirk lyeth, as His Majesties Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, signed with his Royal hand at <hi>White-hall,</hi> the 3. of <hi>January</hi> last, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate in the books of Assembly, this day at length beares. And suchlike wheras the Lords of Exchequer upon a Petition presented to them by the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly, and the Procurator and Agent for the Kirk representing two Prejudices; one, that gifts obtained from His Majestie of patronages of Kirks, at His Presentation were passing the Exchequer, without the qualification and provision of a List, wherewith His Majestie was pleased to restrict Himself; and the other, that some were seeking gifts of patronage of Bishop-Kirks, which are declared to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Presbyteries, to be planted by two Acts of the late Parliament: The saids Lords have ordained that no signator, containing gifts of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronages from His Majestie, shall passe hereafter, but with a speciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision that the same shall be lyable to the tenor of His Majesties said De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration. Ordaining also the Procurator and Agent of the Kirk to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertised, and to have place to see all signators whatsoever, containing any patronage, to the effect they may represent the interest of the Kirk there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; as the said Act of the date the 27. of <hi>June</hi> last, registrate also in the Books of Assembly, this day at length beares. Therefore, that the saids
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:205458:18"/>Kirks which now are, or which were at His Majesties presentation the said third day of <hi>January</hi> last, may be the better provided with able Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, when the samine shall vaik, The Assembly ordaines that hereafter every Presbyterie shall give up yearly a Roll of the ablest of their Expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, to their Synods; and that the Synods select out of these Rolls such persons whom they in certain knowledge judge most fit for the Ministrie, and worthiest of the first place, With Power to the Synods to adde or alter these Rolls given by the Presbyteries, as they thinke reasonable: And that the Synods shall send the Rolls made by them in this manner, to the next Generall Assembly, who shall also examine the Rolls of the Synods, and adde or alter the same as shall be thought expedient. Which Roll made by the Generall Assembly, shall be sent to every Presbyterie, and that the Presbyterie, with consent of the most or best part of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, shall make a List of six persons willing to accept of the presentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of that Roll of the Assembly, upon every occasion of vacation of any Kirk within their bounds, and shall send the famine, together with a blank presentation: The which (if His Majesty be Patron to the vacant Kirk) shall be sent by the said Procurator and Agent, to such as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners of the Generall Assembly, or in their absence the Presbyteie of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> shall direct and think at that time most able and willing to obtain the presentation, to be signed and filled up by His Majesties choise of one of the List. And if the vacant Kirk be of a Patronage disponed by His Majesty since the 3. of <hi>January,</hi> in that case either the Presbyteries themselves shall send a List of six persons in maner aforesaid, with a blank presentation to the Patron, to be filled up by his choise, and subscribed, or send the samine to the saids Officers of the Kirk, to be conveyed by them to the Patron of the vaiking Kirk, as the Presbyterie shall think most expedient. It is alwayes declared, that this order shall be without prejudice to the Presbyteries, with consent foresaid, to put actuall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters upon the said List of six persons, to be sent to the Patron of the said vaiking Kirks, if they please. And least that the nomination of Expectants by Presbyteries, Synods, or Assemblies, in their Rolls or Lists foresaid, be mis-interpreted, as though the Expectants nominated in these Rolls and Lists, were thereby holden and acknowledged to be qualified, which is not the intention of the Assembly, who rather think, that in respect of this Order, there should be a more exact tryall of Expectants then before: Therefore the Assembly ordaines, That no Expectants shall be put on the Rolls or Lists above-mentioned, but such as have been upon the publike exercise, at the least by the space of half a year, or longer, as the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie shall finde necessary. And suchlike ordaines, that hereafter none be admitted to the publike exercise, before they betrayed, according to the tryall appointed for Expectants, at their entrie to the Ministerie in the late Assembly at <hi>Glasgow,</hi> in the 24. Article of the Act of the 23. Session there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: which tryall, the Assembly appoints to be taken of every Expectant, before his admission to the publike exercise. And suchlike ordaines, That the samine tryall shall be again taken immediatly before their admission to the Ministerie, together with their tryall mentioned in the advice of some Brethren deputed for penning the corruptions of the Ministery, approven
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:205458:19"/>in the said Act of the Generall Assembly at <hi>Glasgow.</hi> And because that Kirks of the patronages foresaids, will vaik before the Rolls and Lists be made up by the Presbyteries, Synods, and Generall Assemblies, in manner foresaid: Therefore in the <hi>interim</hi> the Assembly ordains the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of every Presbyterie here present, to give in a List of the ablest Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctants within their bounds, the morn, to the Clerk of the Assembly, that the Assembly may out of these Rolls, make a List to be sent to every Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie: Out of which the Presbyteries shall make a List of six persons, with consent foresaid, and send the famine upon vacancie of any Church within their bounds, together with a presentation to His Majestie, or any other patron, in manner foresaid. And because the Procurator and Agent of the Kirk cannot get sufficient information to the Lords of Exchequer, anent the Right and Interest of the Kirk, and Presbyteries in Kirks, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of gifts of patronages may be presented to the Exchequer: Therefore the Assembly ordaines for their better information hereanent, that every Presbyterie, with all diligence, use all meanes of exact tryall of the nature and qualitie of all Kirks within their bounds, as what Kirks belong to the Kings Majesties patronage, what to other Laick patronages, what Kirks of old were planted by Presbyteries, and what by Prelates, and Bishops, before the Assembly at <hi>Glasgow</hi> 1638. what hath been the way and time of the change of the planting and providing of the Kirks, if any have been changed or any other thing concerning the nature and qualitie of every Kirk within their bounds, and to send the same to the Procurator of the Kirk with all diligence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act anent Lists for the Kirks in the High-lands.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly considering that in <hi>Argyle,</hi> and in other places of the <hi>Irish</hi> language, there will not be gotten six expectants able to speak that language, And therfore the Assembly is hopefull, that in these singular cases, His Majestie will be pleased for Kirks vacand in the <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> to accept of a List of so many expectants as can be had, able to speak the <hi>Irish</hi> language. And the Commissioners Grace promiseth to recommend it to His Majestie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="overtures">
               <head>Overtures against Papists, non-Communicants, and profaners of the Sabbach.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly would draw up a Supplication to be presented by the Commissioners of the Presbyterie of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to the Councell at their first meeting, for the due execution of the Acts of Parliament and Councell against Papists, wherein it will be specially craved, that the Exchequer should be the Intromettors with the Rents of these who are excommunicate, and that from the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer the Presbyterie may receive that portion of the confiscate goods, which the Law appoints to be imployed <hi>ad pios usus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:205458:19"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Every Presbyterie would conveen at their first meeting, all known Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists in their bounds, and require them to put out of their company, all friends and servants who are Popish within one moneth: also within that same space, to give their children, sons and daughters, who are above seven yeers old, to be educate at their charges, by such of their Protestant friends, as the Presbyterie shall approve, and finde sufficient caution for bringing home within three moneths such of their children who are without the Kingdom, to be educate in Schooles and Colledges at the Presbyteries sight; to finde caution likewise of their abstinence from Masse; and the company of all Jesuits and Priests.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> That all, of whatsoever rank or degree, who refuse to give satisfaction in every one of the foresaid Articles, shall be Processed without any delay; but those who give satisfaction shall be dealt with in all meeknesse, after this manner: The Presbyteries shall appoint such of their number as they shall find fittest to confer with them so frequently as the Brethren are able to attend, untill the midst of October next, against which time, if they be not willing to go to Church, they shall give assurance to go and dwell in the next adjacent University Town, whether <hi>Edinburgh, Glasgow, S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> or <hi>Aberdene,</hi> from Novemb. 1. to the last of March, where they shall attend all the diets of conference which the professors and Ministers of the bounds shal appoint to them: by which if they be not converted, their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinacy shal be declared in the Provincial Synods of April, and from thence their Processe shall go on to the very closure without any farther delay. </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> That every Presbyterie, as they will be answerable to the next Generall Assembly, be carefull to do their dutie in all the premisses.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> That there be given presently by the members of this present Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly unto the Commissioners of the Presbyterie of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> a List of all excommunicate Papists they know, and of all Papists who have children educate abroad, that they may be presented, together with our Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the Councell, at their first sitting.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> That the Councell may be supplicate for an Act, that in no Regiment which goes out of the Kingdom, any Papists bear office, and that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell be required to finde caution for this effect, before he receive the Councels Warrant for levying any Souldiers: also that he finde caution for the maintaining of a Minister, and keeping of a Session in his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> the Assembly would enjoyn every Presbyterie to proceed against non-Communicants, whether Papists or others, according to the Act of Parliament made thereanent. And suchlike, that Acts of Parliament against prophaners of the Sabbath be put to execution.</p>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Assembly approves the Overtures foresaid, and ordains Presbyteries to put the samine to execution with all diligence: and that the Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners of every Presbyterie give in a List of the excommunicate Papists within their bounds, and of Papists children out of the Countrey, to the Clerk, that the same may be presented to the Councell by the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of this Assembly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:205458:20"/>
               <head>Act anent the joyning of the Presbyterie of <hi>Sky</hi> to the Synode of <hi>Argyle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall Assembly having considered the whole proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Commissioners of the late Generall Assembly hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> anent the reference made to them concerning the Presbyterie of <hi>Sky,</hi> together with the whole reasons <hi>pro &amp; contra</hi> in the said matter, after mature deliberation have ratified and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and by these presents ratifie and approve the Sentence of the saids Commissioners thereintill. And further ordains the said Presbytery of <hi>Sky,</hi> and all the Ministers and Elders thereof, to keep the meetings of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Assembly of <hi>Argyle,</hi> where they shall happen to be appointed in all time coming, suchlike as any other Presbyterie within the bounds of the said Province of <hi>Argyle</hi> uses to do: And that the samine Presbyterie be in all time hereafter within the jurisdiction of the said Provincial Assembly, without any further question to be made thereanent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. VIII. 3. <hi>Aug. post meridiem.</hi> The Supplication of this Assembly to the KINGS MAjESTIE.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the Kings most Excellent Majestie, the hearty thanksgiving, and humble Petition of the Generall Assembly of the Kirk of</hi> Scotland, <hi>met at</hi> S. Andrews <hi>July</hi> 27. 1642.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur hearts were filled with great joy and gladnesse at the hearing of Your Majesties Letter, which was read once and again in face of the Assembly, every line thereof al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most either expressing such affection to the reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and such royall care of us, as we could require from a Christian Prince; or requiring such necessary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from us, as we are bound to performe as Ministers of the Gospel, and Christian Subjects: For which, as solemne thanks were given by the Moderator of the Assembly, so do we all with one voice in all humility, present unto Your Majestie the thankfulnesse of our hearts, with our ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest prayers to God for your Majesties prosperity, and the peace of Your Kingdoms, that Your Majestie may be indeed a nursing Father to all the Kirks of Christ in Your Majesties Dominions; and especially to the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> honoured with Your Birth and Baptisme: promising our most serious indeavours by doctrine and life, to advance the Gospel of Christ,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:205458:20"/>and to keep the people in our charge in Unity and Peace, and in all loyalty and obedience to Your Majestie and Your Laws. Your Majesties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to Your Commissioner, the Earle of <hi>Dumfermling,</hi> to receive from us our just and reasonable desires for what may further serve for the good of Religion here, the favours which we have received already, and Your Majesties desire and delight to do good, expressed in Your Letter, are as many encouragements to us, to take the boldnesse in all humility to present unto Your Majestie (beside the particulars recommended to Your Majesties Commissioner) one thing, which for the present is the chiefest of all Our desires, as serving most for the glory of Christ, for Your Majesties Honour and Comfort; and not onely for the good of Religion here, but for the true happinesse and peace of all Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Dominions; which is no new motion, but the prosecution of that same which was made by the Commissioners of this Your Majesties Kingdom in the late Treatie, and which Your Majestie, with advice of both Houses of Parliament, did approve in these words: <hi>To their desire concerning unitie in Religion and uniformitie of Church government, as a speciall meanes of conserving of Peace betwixt the two Kingdoms, upon the grounds and reasons contained in the Paper of the</hi> 10. <hi>of</hi> March, <hi>given in to the Treaty and Parliament of</hi> England: It is answered upon the 15 of <hi>June, That His Majestie, with advice of both Houses of Parliament, doth approve of the affection of His Subjects of</hi> Scotland, <hi>in their desire of having the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of Church-government betwixt the two Nations, and as the Parliament hath already taken into consideration the reformation of Church government, so they will proceed therein in due time, as shall best conduce to the glory of God, the Peace of the Church, and of both Kingdoms,</hi> 11. <hi>of</hi> June 1641. In Our Answer to a Declaration sent by the now Commissioners of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from both Houses of Parliament, we have not onely pressed this point of unity in Religion and Uniformity of Church-government, as a meane of a firme and durable union betwixt the two Kingdomes, and without which former experiences put us out of hope long to enjoy the puritie of the Gospel with Peace, but also have rendred the reasons of our hopes and confidence, as from other considerations, so from Your Majesties late Letter to this Assembly, that Your Majestie in a happy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the Houses of Parliament, will be pleased to settle this bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Reformation, with so earnestly desired a Peace in all Your Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And therfore we Your Majesties most loving Subjects, in name of the whole Kirks of <hi>Scotland,</hi> represented by us, upon the knees of our hearts, do most humbly and earnestly beg, that Your Majesty in the deep of Your Royall Wisdom, and from Your affection to the true Religion, and the Peace of Your Kingdoms, may be moved to consider, that the God of Heaven and Earth is calling for this Reformation at Your hands, and that as you are his Vice-gerent, so You may be his prime Instrument in it. If it shall please the Lord (which is our desire and hope) that this bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed unitie in Religion and Uniformity in Government shall be brought about; Your Majesties Conscience, in performing of so great a dutie, shall be a well-spring of comfort to Your Self, Your memory shall be a sweet favour, and Your name renowned to all following generations. And
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:205458:21"/>if these unhappy commotions and divisions shall end in this peace and unity, then it shall appeare in the Providence of God, they were but the noyse of many waters, and the voyce of a great thunder before the voyce of harpers harping with their harps, which shall fill this whole Iland with melodie and mirth, and the name of it shall be, THE LORD IS THERE.</p>
               <div type="declaration">
                  <head>The Declaration of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> sent to the Assembly.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lords and Commons in this present Parliament assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, finding to their great grief, that the distractions of this Kingdome daily increase, and that the wicked counsells and practises of a malignant party amongst us (if God prevent them not) are like to cast this nation into bloud &amp; confusion, To testifie to all the World how earnestly they desire to avoid a Civill Warre, they have addressed themselves in an humble Supplication to His Majestie, for the prevention thereof. A Copy of which their Petition, they have thought fit to send at this time to the Nationall Assembly of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the intent that that Church and Kingdome (whereunto they are united by so many and so near bonds and tyes, as well Spirituall as Civill) may see that the like minde is now in them, that formerly appeared to be in that Nation. And that they are as tender of the effusion of Christian bloud on the one side, as they are zealous on the other side of a due Reformation both in Church and State. In which work, whilest they were labouring, they have been interrupted by the plots and practises of a malignant party of Papists, and ill-affected persons, especially of the corrupt and dissolute Clergy, by the incitement and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stigation of Bishops, and others, whose avarice and ambition being not able to bear the Reformation endeavoured by the Parliament, they have laboured (as we can expect little better fruit from such trees) to kindle a flame, and raise a combustion within the bowels of this Kingdom: Which if by our humble supplication to His Majesty it may be prevented, and that according to our earnest desire therein, all Force and Warlike prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations being laid aside, we may returne to a peaceable Parliamentary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, We do not doubt, but that by the blessing of Almighty God upon our endeavours, we shall settle the matters both in Church and State, to the encrease of His Majesties Honour and State, the peace and prosperitie of this Kingdome, and especially to the glory of God, by the advancement of the true Religion, and such a Reformation of the Church, as shall be most agreeable to Gods Word. Out of all which, there will also most undoubtedly result a most firme and stable Union between the two Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> which according to our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation, we shall by all good wayes and meanes, upon all occasions, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to preserve and maintain,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Subscribitur</hi> Jo. Brown <hi>Cler. Parl.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:205458:21"/>
                  <head>The Assemblies Answer to the Declaration of the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall Assembly of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> having received a Declaration sent unto them by the Commissioners of this Kingdome, now at <hi>London,</hi> from the Honourable Houses of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> expressing their care to prevent the effusion of Christian bloud in that Kingdome, and their affections to Reformation both in Kirk and State, and having taken the same to such consideration as the importance of so weighty matters, and the high esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation they have of so wise and honourable a meeting as is the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> did require; have with universall consent resolved upon this following Answer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> That from the recent sense of the goodnesse of God, in their own late deliverance, and from their earnest desire of all happinesse to our native King and that Kingdome, they blesse the Lord for preserving them in the midst of so many unhappy divisions and troubles from a bloudy Intestine War, which is from God the greatest Judgement, and to such a nation the compend of all calamities. They also give God thanks for their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and present desires of a Reformation, especially of Religion, which is the glory and strength of a Kingdome, and bringeth with it all temporall blessings of prosperity and peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> That the hearts of all the members of this Assembly, and of all the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected within this Kingdome, are exceedingly grieved and made heavy, that in so long a time, against the professions both of King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and contrary to the joynt desires and prayers of the godly in both Kingdomes, to whom it is more deare and precious then what is dearest to them in the world, the Reformation of Religion hath moved so slowly, and suffered so great interruption. They consider that not only Prelates, formall Professours, profane and worldly men, and all that are Popishly affected, are bad councellours and workers, and do abuse their power, and bend all their strength and policies against the Work of God; but the God of this world also, with Principalities and Powers, the rulers of the darknesse of this world, and spirituall wickednesse in high places, are work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with all their force and fraud in the same opposition, not without hope of successe, they having prevailed so farre from the beginning, That in the times of the best Kings of <hi>Juda</hi> of old, and the most part of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Kirks of late, a through and perfect Reformation of Religion hath been a work full of difficulties, Yet doe they conceive, that as it ought first of all to be intended, so should it be above all other things, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God, who is greater then the world, and he who is in the world, most seriously endeavoured. And that when the supreame Providence giveth opportunity of the accepted time and day of salvation, no other work can prosper in the hands of his servants, if it be not apprehended, and with all reverence and faithfulnesse improved. This Kirk and Nation, when the Lord gave them the calling, considered not their own deadnesse, nor staggered at the promise through unbelief, but gave glory to God.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:205458:22"/>And who knoweth (we speak it in humility and love, and from no other mind then from a desire of the blessing of God upon our King and that Kingdome) but the Lord hath now some controversie with <hi>England,</hi> which will not be removed, till first and before all, the worship of his name and the government of his house be settled according to his own will? When this desire shall come, it shall be to <hi>England,</hi> after so long deferred hopes, a tree of life, which shall not only yeeld temporall blessings unto themselves, but also shall spread the branches so far, that both this nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and other reformed Kirks shall finde the fruits thereof to their great satisfaction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> The Commissioners of this Kingdome in the late Treaty of peace, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering that Religion is not only the meane of the service of God, and saving of Souls, but is also the base and foundation of Kingdomes and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states, and the strongest band to tye Subjects to their Prince in true loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, and to knit the hearts of one to another in true unity and love, They did with preface of all due respect and reverence, far from arrogancy or presumption, represent in name of this Kingdome, their serious thoughts and earnest desires for unity of Religion, That in all His Majesties Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, there might be one Confession of Faith, one directory of worship, one publike Catechisme, and one form of Kirk Government. This they conceived to be acceptable to God Almighty, who delighteth to see his People walking in truth and unity, to be a speciall meanes for conserving of peace betwixt the Kingdomes, of easing the Kings Majesty, and the publike government of much trouble, which ariseth from differences of Religion, very grievous to Kings and Estates; of great content to the King himself, to his Nobles, his Court, and all his People, when (occasioned to be abroad) without scruple to themselves, or scandall to others, all may resort to the same publike worship, as if they were at their own dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; of suppressing the names of Heresies, and Sects, Puritans, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists, Separatists, Anabaptists, &amp;c. which do rent asunder the bowels both of Kirk and Kingdome; of despaire of successe to Papists and Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants, to have their profession, which is inconsistent with the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion, and authority of Princes, set up again, and of drawing the hearts and hands of Ministers, from unpleasant and unprofitable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies, to the pressing of mortification, and to Treatises of true pietie, and practicall Divinity. The Assembly doth now enter upon the labour of the Commissioners, unto which they are encouraged, not only by their faithfulnesse in the late Treaty, but also by the zeale and example of the Generall Assemblies of this Kirk in former times, as may appeare by the Assembly at <hi>Edinburgh, Decemb.</hi> 25. in the year 1566. which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a Letter to be sent to <hi>England</hi> against the Surplice, Tippet, Corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cap, and such other Ceremonies as then troubled that Kirk, that they might be removed. By the Assembly at <hi>Edinburgh, April</hi> 24. 1583. humbly desiring the Kings Majesty, to command his Ambassadour, then going to <hi>England,</hi> to deale with the Queen, that there might be an Union and Band, betwixt them and other Christian Princes and Realmes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing the true Religion for defence and protection of the Word of God, and Professors thereof, against the persecution of Papists and confederates
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:205458:22"/>joyned and united together by the bloudy league of <hi>Trent:</hi> as also that her Majesty would disburden their brethren of <hi>England</hi> of the yoke of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, imposed upon them, against the liberty of the Word: And by the Assembly at <hi>Edinburgh, March</hi> 3. 1589. ordaining the Presbyterie of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to use all good and possible means for the relief and comfort of the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> then heavily troubled for the maintaining the true discipline and government of the Kirk, and that the Brethren in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and publike prayers, recommend the estate of the afflicted Kirk of <hi>England</hi> to God. While now by the mercy of God the conjunction of the two Kingdomes is many wayes increased, the zeale of the Generall Assembly towards their happinesse ought to be no lesse. But besides these, the Assembly is much encouraged unto this duetie, both from the Kings Majesty and his Parliament, joyntly, in their Answer to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, made by the late Commissioners of the Treaty, in these words: <hi>To their desire concerning unity of Religion, and uniformity of Kirk govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a speciall meanes for conserving of peace betwixt the two Kingdomes, upon the grounds and reasons contained in the paper of the</hi> 10 <hi>of</hi> March, <hi>and given in to the Treatie and Parliament of</hi> England: <hi>It is answered upon the</hi> 15. <hi>of</hi> June, <hi>That his Majestie with advice of both Houses of Parliament, doth approve of the affection of His Subjects of</hi> Scotland, <hi>in their desire of having conformitie of Kirk-government between the two Nations, and as the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath already taken into consideration the Reformation of Kirk-government, so they will proceed therein in due time, as shall best conduce to the glory of God, the peace of the Kirk, and of both Kingdomes.</hi> And also severally: for His Majestie knoweth that the custodie and vindication, the conservation and purgation of Religion, are a great part of the duetie of Civill authority and power. His Majesties late practise while he was here in person, in resorting frequently to the exercises of publike worship, His Royall actions, in establishing the worship and government of this Kirk in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in giving order for a competent maintenance to the Ministery and Seminaries of the Kirk, and His Majesties gracious Letter to the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly (seconded by the speech of His Majesties Commissioner) which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines this religious expression: <hi>Where any thing is amisse, we will endeavour a Reformation in a fair and orderly way, and where Reformation is settled, we resolve with that authority wherewith God hath vested us, to maintain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it in peace and liberty, against all trouble that can come from without, and against all Heresies, Sects, and Schismes, which may arise from within.</hi> All these doe make us hopefull that His Majestie will not oppose, but advance the work of Reformation. In like manner the Honourable Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as they have many times before witnessed their zeale, so now also in their Declaration sent to the Assembly, which not only sheweth the constancy of their zeale, but their great grief that the worke hath been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted by a malignant party of Papists and evill affected persons, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the corrupt and dissolute Clergie, by the incitement and instigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Bishops and others, their hope according to their earnest desire, when they shall returne to a peaceable and Parliamentary proceeding, by the blessing of God, to settle such a Reformation in the Church, as shall be agreeable to Gods word, and that the result shall be a most firm and stable
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:205458:23"/>union between the two Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. The As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly also is not a little encouraged by a Letter sent from many reverend Brethren of the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> expressing their prayers and endeavours against every thing which shall be found prejudiciall to the establishment of the Kingdome of Christ, and the Peace of their Soveraigne. Upon these encouragements, and having so patent a doore of hope, the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly doth confidently expect, that <hi>England</hi> will now bestirre themselves in the best way for a Reformation of Religion, and do most willingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their prayers and uttermost endeavours for furthering so great a Work, wherein Christ is so much concerned in his glory, the King in his honour, the Kirk and Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> in their happinesse, and this Kirk and Kingdome in the purity and peace of the Gospel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> That the Assembly also from so many reall invitations, are heartened to renew the Proposition made by the aforenamed Commissioners of this Kingdome, for begining the Work of Reformation, at the uniformity of Kirk-government. For what hope can there be of Unity in Religion, of one Confession of Faith, one Form of Worship, and one Catechisme, till there be first one Forme of Ecclesiasticall Government? Yea, what hope can the Kingdome and Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> have of a firme and durable Peace, till Prelacie, which hath been the main cause of their miseries and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, first and last, be plucked up, root and branch, as a plant which God hath not planted, and from which, no better fruits can be expected then such sower grapes, as this day set on edge the Kingdome of <hi>England?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> The Prelaticall Hierarchie being put out of the way, the Work will be easie, without forcing of any conscience, to settle in <hi>England</hi> the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Reformed Kirks by Assemblies. For although the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Kirks do hold, without doubting, their Kirk Officers, and Kirk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government by Assemblies higher and lower, in their strong and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full subordination, to be <hi>jure divino,</hi> and perpetuall: yet Prelacie, as it differeth from the Office of a Pastor, is almost universally acknowledged by the Prelates themselves, and their adherents, to be but an humane or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, introduced by humane reason, and settled by humane Law and Custome for supposed conveniecie: which therefore by humane autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, without wronging any mans conscience, may be altred and abolished upon so great a necessity, as is a hearty conjunction with all the Reformed Kirks, a firm and well grounded Peace betwixt the two Kingdomes, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly divided in themselves, &amp; betwixt themselves by this partition wall, and a perfect Union of the Kirks in the two Nations: which although by the providence of God in one Iland, and under one Monarch, yet ever since the Reformation, and for the present also, are at greater difference in the point of Kirk-government, which in all places hath a powerfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon all the parts of Religion, then any other Reformed Kirks, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in Nations at greatest distance, and under divers Princes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> What may be required of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for furthering the Work of Uniformitie of Government, or for agreeing upon a common Confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Faith, Catechisme, and directory for Worship, shall according to the order given by this Assembly, be most willingly performed by Us, who long extreamly for the day when King and Parliament shall joyn for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:205458:23"/>bringing to passe so great, so good a Work, That all Warres and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions ceasing, all Superstition, Idolatry, Heresie, Sects, and Schismes being removed, as the Lord is one, so his name may be one amongst us; and mercy and truth, righteousnesse and peace meeting together, and kis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing one another, may dwell in this Iland.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act Sess. VIII. <hi>Aug.</hi> 3. 1642.</head>
               <p>Overtures for transplantation of Ministers, &amp; provision of Schools, ordained by the late Assembly at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to be sent to Synods, and reported to this Assembly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act Sess XI. <hi>Edinb.</hi> Aug. 5. 1641.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>These Overtures underwritten, anent the transporting of Ministers and Professors to Kirks and Colledges, being read in audience of the Assembly, and thereafter revised by a Committee appointed for that effect, The Assembly appoints them to be sent to the severall Synods, to be considered by them, and they to report their judgements thereof to the next Generall Assembly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O transportation would be granted hereafter without citation of parties having interest (<hi>viz.</hi> the Minister who is sought and his Parish) to hear what they can oppose, and the matter is to come first to both the Presbyteries (<hi>viz.</hi> that wherein the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister dwels, whose transportation is sought, and the other Presbyterie to which he is sought if the Kirks lye in several Presbyteries) and if the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries agree not, then the matter is to be brought to the Synod, or Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Assembly (which of them shall first occure after such transportation is sought) and if the Synod (occurring first) agree not; or if there be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale made from it, then the matter is to come to the Generall Assembly. </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> A Minister may be transplanted from a particular Congregation (where he can onely doe good to a part) to such a place, where he may benefit the whole Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> because, in reason the whole is to be preferred to a part, such as <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Because all the great Justice Courts sit there, as Councell, Session, Justice Generall, Exchequer, &amp;c. and it concerns the whole Kirk, that these Fountains of Justice be kept clean, both in the point of Faith, and Manners.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Because there is great confluence to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> from time to time, of many of the chief Members of the whole Kingdome, and it concerns the whole Kirk to have these well seasoned, who (apparantly) are to be the Instruments of keeping this Kirk and Kingdome in good temper.</p>
               <p>That this may be the more easily done, the Assembly first recommends to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> that some young men of excellent spirits may be (upon the charges of the said Town) trained up, at home or abroad, toward the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery from time to time. Secondly we meane not, that all the places of the Ministerie of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> be filled with Ministers to be transported
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:205458:24"/>by Authority of this Act, but only till they be provided of one Minister (transplanted by the Authority of the Assembly) for every Kirk in <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and that the rest of the places be filled either according to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Rules of transportation for the whole Kingdome, or by agreement with actuall Ministers, and their Parishes, with consent of the Presbyterie or Synod, to the which they belong.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> In the next roome, we finde, that it is a transporting of Ministers for publike good, that Colledges, (having the profession of Divinitie) be well provided of Professors.</p>
               <p>Wherein the Colledge of Divinitie in S. <hi>Andrews</hi> is first to be served, without taking any Professors or Ministers out of <hi>Edinburgh, Glasgow,</hi> or <hi>Aberdene,</hi> and then the rest of the Colledges, would be provided for, as their necessity shall require: yet (in respect of the present scarcity) it were good for the Universities to send abroad for able and approved men, to be Professors of Divinitie, that our Ministers may be kept in their pastorall charge asmuch as may be.</p>
               <p>Towns also wherein Colledges are, are very considerable in the matter of transportation.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> Also Congregations, where Noblemen have chief residence are to be regarded, whether planted or unplanted, and a care is to be had, that none be admitted Ministers where Popish Noblemen reside, but such as are able men (especially for controversies) by sight of the Presbyterie: and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over it is necessary, that such Ministers as dwell where Popish Noblemen are, and are not able for controversies, that they be transported.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> They who desire the transportation of a Minister should be obliged to give reasons for their desire: Neither should any Presbyterie or Assembly, passe a sentence for transportation of any Minister, till they give reasons for the expediencie of the same, both to him and his Congregation, and to the Presbyterie whereof he is a member. If they acquiesce to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons given, it is so much the better: if they doe not acquiesce, yet the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie, or Assembly, (by giving such reasons before the passing of their sentence) shall make it manifest, that what they doe is not <hi>pro arbitratu, vel imperio</hi> onely, but upon grounds of reason.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> Because there is such scarcity of Ministers having the <hi>Irish</hi> tongue, neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity requires, that when they be found in the Low-lands, they be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the High-lands: providing their condition be not made worse, but rather better by their transportation.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> In the point of voluntary transportation, no Minister shall transact and agree with any Parish, to be transported thereto, without a full hearing of him, and his Parish, before the Presbyterie to which he belongs in his present charge, or superiour Kirk judicatories, if need shall be.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VIII"/> The planting of vacant Kirks, is not to be tyed to any (either Ministers, or Expectants) within a Presbyterie: but a free election is to be, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the order of our Kirk, and Lawes of our Kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IX"/> The chief Burghs of the Kingdome are to be desired to traine up young men of excellent spirits for the Ministery, according to their power, as was recommended to <hi>Edinburgh:</hi> Which course will in time (God willing) prevent many transplantations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="overtures">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:205458:24"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Overtures under-written anent the Schooles being likewise read in audience of the Assembly, they recommend the particulars therein mentioned, anent the providing of the maintenance for School masters, to the Parliament: and ordaine the rest to be sent to the Synods, to be considered by them, and they to report their judgements thereof to the next Generall Assembly, as said is.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very Parish would have a Reader and a Schoole, where chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are to be bred, in reading, writting, and grounds of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to the laudable Acts, both of Kirk and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, made before.</p>
               <p>And where Grammar Schooles may be had, as in Burghs, and other considerable places, (among which all Presbyteriall Seates are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted) that they be erected, and held hand to.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Anent these Schooles, every Minister with his Elders, shall give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt to the Presbyteries at the visitation of the Kirk; the Presbyteries are to make report to the Synode, and the Synode to the Generall Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that Schools are planted, as above-said, and how they are provided with men and means.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> And because this hath been most neglected in the High-lands, Ilands, and borders. Therefore the Ministers of every Parish are to instruct by their Commissioners, to the next Generall Assembly, that this course is begun betwixt and then: and they are further to certifie from one General Assembly to another, whether this course is continued without omission, or not.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> And because the means hitherto named or appointed for Schooles of all sorts, hath been both little, and ill payed, Therefore, beside former appointments, (the execution whereof is humbly desired, and to be peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned for at the hands of His Majestie and the Parliament) the Assembly would further supplicate this Parliament that they (in their wisdome) would finde out how meanes shall be had for so good an use, especially that the children of poore men, (being very capable of learning, and of good engines) may be trained up, according as the exigence and necessity of evey place shall require. And that the Commissioners, who shall be named by this Assembly, to wait upon the Parliament, may be appointed to represent this to his Majestie, and the Parliament, seeing His sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie, by His gracious Letter hath put us in hope hereof, wherewith we have been much refreshed.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> The Assembly would supplicate the Parliament, that for youths of the finest and best spirits of the High-lands, and borders, maintenance may be allotted (as to Bursars) to be bred in Universities.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> For the time and manner of visitation of Schooles, and contriving the best and most compendious and orderly course of teaching Grammar, we humbly desire the Assembly to appoint a Committee for that effect, who may report their diligence to the next Generall Assembly.</p>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Overtures and Articles above-written being reported to this Assembly, after reading and serious consideration thereof, the Assembly approves the same, And ordaines them to have the strength of an Act and ordinance of Assembly in all time coming.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:205458:25"/>
               <head>Sess. XI. 5. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642. <hi>Act anent contrary Oaths.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall Assembly finding the inconvenience of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Oaths in trying of Adulteries, Fornications, and other faults and scandals, do therefore for eviting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, discharge Synods, Presbyteries and Sessions, to take Oath of both parties in all time hereafter, Recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them in the mean time all other order and wayes of tryall used in such cases: And that there may be a common order and course kept in this Kirk of trying of publike scandals, The Assembly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains the Presbyteries to advise upon some common order hereintill, and to report their judgements to the next Assembly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="overtures">
               <head>Overtures anent Family Exercises, Catechising, keeping of Synods and Presbyteries, and restraint of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, Witch-crafts, and other grosse sins.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Committee supplicates the Assembly,</head>
               <p n="1">I. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O urge the severall Synods and Presbyteries, especially these of the North, that Family Exercise in Religion, visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Churches, Catechising, keeping of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall and Provinciall meetings (both by Preaching and Ruling Elders) be more carefully observed.</p>
               <p n="2">II. That the Clerk at least subscribe every Book before it come to the Assembly, and that every Act be noted on the Margent, for a directory of expedition.</p>
               <p n="3">III. That the Assembly would seriously studie by all meanes and wayes how to procure the Magistrates concurrence to curb and punish these notorious vices which abound in the Land, especially in the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern parts.</p>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Assembly approves the Overtures foresaids, and ordains them to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served: and for the last, the Assembly being confident of the readinesse of the Judge Ordinar to restrain and punish these faults, Do therefore ordain all Presbyteries to give up to the Justice, the names of the Adulterers, incestuous persons, Witches and Sorcerers, and others guilty of such grosse and fearfull sins within their bounds, that they may be Processed, and punished according to the Laws of this Kingdom; and that the Presbyteries and Synods be carefull herein, as they will answer to the Generall Assemblies. And because that Witch-craft, Charming, and such like, proceeds many times from ignorance; Therefore the Assembly ordains all Ministers, especially in these parts where these sins are frequent, to be diligently Preaching, Catechising, and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, to inform their people thereintill.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:205458:25"/>
               <head>Sess. XI. 5. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642. <hi>Act against Petitions, Declarations, &amp; such like in name of Ministers, without their knowledge and consents.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall Assembly being informed, that after the Petition presented to the Lords of His Majesties Privie Councell by the Noblemen Burgesses, and Ministers, occasionally met at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the 31. day of <hi>May</hi> last by past, had received a very gracious Answer, There was another Petition given in to their Lordships upon the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> day of <hi>June</hi> last, entituled, The Petition of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Gentrie, Burrows, Ministers, and Commons: which as it was not accompanied with any one Minister to the Lords of Privie Councell, so all the Ministers of this Assembly, disclaimes and disavow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, or accession thereto. And the Assembly conceiving that the Kings Majestie Himself, and all the Courts and Judicatories of this Kingdome may be deluded and abused, and the Kirk in Generall, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters in particular injured and prejudged by the like practises hereafter, Do therefore prohibite and discharge all and every one to pretend or use the name of Ministers to any Petition, Declaration, or such like at any time hereafter, without their knowledge, consent and assistance: And if any shall doe the contrary, ordaines Presbyteries and Provinciall Assemblies to proceed against them with the highest censures of the Kirk.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. XI. 5. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642. <hi>Act anent the Assemblies desires to the Lords of Counsell, and Conservators of Peace.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly being most desirous to use all, and to omit no lawfull meane or occasion to testifie their zeale by dealing with God and man, for furtherance of their desires of Unity in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and uniformity of Kirk-government, And considering the great necessity, that the Kirk and State contribute jointly their best endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to this happy end: Therefore enjoynes the Moderator, and the Commissioners from the Assembly, to supplicate with all earnestnesse and respect, the Lords of his Majesties Honourable Privie Councell, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the Commissioners appointed by His Majestie, and the Parliament, for conservation of the Peace, that they may be pleased to concur with the Kirk in the like desires to His Majesty and the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and in the like directions to the Commissioners of this Kingdome, at <hi>London</hi> for the time, that by all possible means, Civill, and Ecclesiastick, this blessed Worke may be advanced, and a happy settling betwixt His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie and His Parliament, may be endeavoured, and the common Peace betwixt the Kingdomes continued and strengthened.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:205458:26"/>
               <head>Sess. XI. <hi>Aug.</hi> 5. 1642. <hi>The Assemblies humble desire to the Kings Majestie for the Signator of</hi> 500 l. <hi>Sterling, and recommendation thereof to the Kings Commissioner.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall Assembly having received the Report of the proceedings of the Commissioners of the late Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and specially that His Majesty was graciously plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, upon their humble Petition, solemnly to promise and declare under his Royall hand, his pious resolution and dedication of 500. l. sterling, out of the readiest of his Rents and revenues, to be imployed yearly on publike necessary and pious uses of the Kirk, at the sight of the Generall Assembly, as His Majesties gracious Answer of the 3. of <hi>January,</hi> 1642. registrate in their books at His Majesties own desire, for their further assurance of His Majesties pious zeale, doth more fully proport. Likeas being informed that His Majestie was gratiously pleased to signe and send down to the Kirk the Signator of the said 500. l. yearly to have past the Exchequer, albeit the famine is not as yet delivered; And considering His Majesties pious dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to them by his Majesties Letter to plant and visit the utmost skirts and borders of the Kingdome, as most necessary for the glory of God, the good of the Kirk, and His Majesties honour, and service, which is only stopped by the want of charges for publike visitations, And withall to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate to His Majestie by His Commissioner, their just and necessary desires for what may further serve to the good of Religion, whereunto His Majesties Commissioner promised his best endeavours and assistance. Therefore the Assembly doth most earnestly recommend to His Majesties Commissioner to represent to His Majestie, with his best assistance, the humble and necessary desires of the whole Assembly, that His Majestie wil be graciously pleased to command that Signator, already signed by His Royall hand (or to signe another of the samine tenor, whereof they deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the just double to His Majesties Commissioner for that effect) to be sent to this Kingdom, and delivered to the Commissioners from this As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly, who are to sit at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> or to the Procurator of the Kirk, whereby His Majestie shall more and more oblige this whole Kirk to pray for a blessing from Heaven upon His Royall Person and Government.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:205458:26"/>
               <head>Sess. XI. 5. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642. <hi>The Assemblies Letter to the Commissioners of this Kingdom at</hi> London.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E have received your Lordships Letter, with the Declaration of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and have sent this Noble bearer to His Majesty with our humble Supplication, and to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships with our Answer, earnestly desiring Unity of Religion, and Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Kirk-government, to be presented by your Lordships, and this Noble bearer to the Honourable Houses of Parliament. Your Lordships will perceive by the inclosed Copies, and by our desires to His Majesties honourable Privie Councell and Commissioners for the conservation of the Peace, to joyn their best endeavours with His Majestie and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and their directions to your Lordships, by our leaving a Commission behinde us, to concur with them in all Ecclesiastick wayes, and by our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing publike Prayers, and a solemn Fast through this Kirk, for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of this great work of Reformation, and continuance of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Peace, that this unity in Religion &amp; Uniformity of Kirk-government is the chiefest of our desires, prayers and cares: whereunto as we have been encouraged by the faithfull labors of the Commissioners of this Kingdom in the late Treaty, and continued and renewed by your Lordships; so we are assured, that your Lordships will omit no lawfull mean, argument, or occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of seconding the same there, And advertising our Commissioners at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> wherein they may further concur with your Lordships, for the furtherance of the Work, which tends so much to the glory of God, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Christs Kingdom, increase of the honour and happinesse of our Soveraign, and the peace and welfare of these Kingdoms, whereby your Lordships will oblige this Kirk more and more to pray for a blessing on your persons and travels, and to rest</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours in the Lord The Commissioners of the Generall Assembly.</signed>
                  <dateline>S. Andrews <date>5. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter from some Ministers of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend and wel-beloved in our Lord and Saviour,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E received with much joy and satisfaction, the Answer which your Generall Assembly vouchsafed us to our Letters of the last yeer. Some of us in the name of our Brethren thought it then fit by M. <hi>Alexander Henderson</hi> (a Brother so justly approved by you, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by us) to return our deserved thanks. And we now further think it equall upon this occasion, to make a more publike acknowledgement of such a publike favour. You were then pleased to give us fair grounds, to expect that brotherly advice and endeavours, which the common cause of Christ, and the mutuall interest of the united Nations, command us now again to ask, if not to chalenge. We doubt not but your experience, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:205458:27"/>with your intelligence, abundantly informes you of our condition, what various administrations of providence we have passed through, and we still lye betwixt hopes and feares, a fit temper for working; the God of all grace enable us to improve it. As our hopes are not such as may make us fear, so neither doe our Feares prevail, to the casting away our confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Your own late condition, together with this Declaration of ours present, may acquaint you with the certain, though subtil, authors and fomentors of these our confused conflicts: which we conceive to be the Hierarchical faction, who have no way to peace and safety, but through the trouble and danger of others. Our prayers and endeavours, according to our measure, have been, and shall be for the supplanting and rooting up whatsoever we finde so prejudiciall to the establishment of the Kingdome of Christ, and the peace of our Soveraigne. And that this Declaration of our selves may not leave you unsatisfied, we think it necessary further to expresse, That the desire of the most godly and considerable part amongst us, is, That the Presbyterian Government, which hath just and evident Foundation both in the Word of God, and religious reason, may be established amongst us, and that (according to your intimation) we may agree in one Confession of Faith, one directorie of Worship, one publike Catechisme and form of government: Which things, if they were accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished, we should much rejoyce in our happy subjection to Christ our Head, and our desired association with you our beloved brethren. For the better effecting whereof, we thought it necessary, not only to acquaint you with what our desires are in themselves, but likewise to you, that is, That what way shall seem most fit to the wisedom of that grave and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Assembly, may be taken for the furtherance of our indeavours in this kind. We understand that our Parliament hath been beforehand with us in this intimation, and it cannot but be our duty, who are so much concerned in the businesse, to adde what power the Lord hath given us with you to the same purpose. This designe and desire of ours hath enemies on the Left-hand; and dissenting brethren on the Right; but we doubt not, that as our hearts justifie us that our intentions are right, and such as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive tend most to the glory of God, and the peace of the Churches of the Saints; so (by your brotherly concurrence in the most speedy and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all way you can find out) the Work will in Gods due, time receive a prayed for, hoped for issue. We shall not need by many arguments from mutuall Nationall interest (though we know you will not overlook them) to inforce this request, the firme bond wherewith we are all united in our Lord Jesus Christ, we are assured will alone engage your faithfull endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors in this businesse. To him we commit you, with these great and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant affairs you have in hand. Be pleased to accept of these as the expression of the mindes of our many godly and faithfull Brethren, whose hearts we doubt not of, neither need you, though their hands in regard of the sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dennesse of this opportunity could not be subscribed together with ours, who are</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your most affectionate friends and brethren in the Work of the Lord.</signed>
                  <dateline>London <date>22. <hi>July</hi> 1642.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:205458:27"/>
               <head>Answer to the Ministers Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Reverend and beloved in the Lord Jesus.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y our Answer to the Declaration sent unto us from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houses of Parliament, ye may perceive that your Letter which came into our hands so seasonably, was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acceptable unto us, but hath also encouraged us to renew both to the Kings Majestie and the Houses of Parliament, The desires of the late Commissioners of this Kingdome for Unity in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, in the four particulars remembred by you, we cannot be ignorant but the opposition from Satan and worldly men in Kirk and Policy, will still be vehement as it hath been already, But we are confident through our Lord Jesus Christ, that the prayers and indeavours of the godly in both Kingdoms, will bring the work to a wished, and blessed Issue. This whole nationall Kirk is so much concerned in that Reformation and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Religion in both Kingdomes, that without it we cannot hope for any long time to enjoy our puritie and peace, which hath cost us so dear, and is now our chiefest comfort and greatest treasure: Which one cause (beside the Honour of God, and the happinesse of the People of God in that Kingdome, more desired of us then Our lives) is more then sufficient to move us, To contribute all that is in our power for bringing it to passe. And since we have with so great liberty made our desires and hopes known both to King and Parliament, it is a duety incumbent both to you and us, who make mention of the Lord, and are Watch-men upon the Walls of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> never more to keep silence nor to hold our peace day nor night, till the righteousnesse of Sion go forth as brightnesse, and the salvation thereof as a lamp that burneth. And if it shall please the Lord to move the hearts of King and Parliament, to hearken unto the motion, for which end we have resolved to keep a solemne Fast and Humiliation in all the Kirks of this Kingdome, the mean by which we have prevailed in times past, we wish that the Work may be begun with speed, and prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted with diligence by the joint labours of some Divines in both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, who may prepare the same for the view and examination of a more frequent Ecclesiastick meeting of the best affected to Reformation there, and of the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly here, that in end it may have the approbation of the Generall Assembly here, and of all the Kirks there, in the best way that may be, we wish and hope at last in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Assembly; Our Commissioners at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> shall in our name re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and returne answers for promoving so great a Work, which we with our heart and our soule recommend to the blessing of God, we continue,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your loving brethren and fellow-labourers.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:205458:28"/>
               <head>Act for the Lord <hi>Maitlands</hi> presenting the Assemblies Supplication to His Majestie, and for going to the Commissioners at <hi>London,</hi> with the Answer to the Parliament of <hi>Englands</hi> Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He General Assembly considering the necessity of sending some person of good worth and quality for to present their humble Supplication to His Majestie, and to deliver their directions to the Commissioners of this Kingdom, now at <hi>London,</hi> with their Declaration to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and Answer to some wel-affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Ministers of that Kirk: And having certain knowledge of the worth, ability, and faithfulnesse of <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> one of their number, who being witnesse to all their intentions and proceedings, can best relate their true loyaltie and respect to their Soveraign, and brotherly affection to the Kirk and Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> therein; Therefore do unanimously require his Lordships pains, by repairing to Court and to <hi>London</hi> for the premisses, which hereby they commit to his diligence and fidelity, willing his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to make account of his proceedings herein to their Commissioners appointed to sit at <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. XII. 5. <hi>Aug. post meridiem. Commission for publike affairs of this Kirk, and for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuting the desires of this Assembly to His Majestie and the Parliament of</hi> England.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall Assembly considering the laudable custome of this Kirk for to appoint some Commissioners in the interim betwixt Assemblies, for presenting of Overtures and prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the other desires of the Kirk to His Majestie, the Lords of His Councell, and the Estates of Parliament; And taking to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration the present condition of the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> with the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof sent down from the Parliament, and some reverend Brethren of the Ministery there, with their own Answer to the Parliament and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery, and their humble Supplication to His Majestie for Unity of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Uniformity of Kirk-government. And withall remembring their desires to the Honourable Lords of His Majesties secret Councell, and to the Commissioners appointed by the King and Parliament, for conserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the common Peace, That they would joyn their concourse in their desires to His Majestie and Parliament, and directions to the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of this Kingdom at <hi>London</hi> for the time. And likewise considering their good hopes from Gods gracious favour to this Island, that by his good providence he will in his own way and time settle this great Work through this whole Ile; And that it is both our earnest desire and Christian duty to use all lawfull means and Ecclesiastick wayes for furtherance of so
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:205458:28"/>great a Work, continuance of the common peace betwixt these nations, and keeping a brotherly correspondence betwixt these Kirks. Therfore the Assembly thinks it necessary before their dissolving, to appoint, &amp; by these presents do nominate and appoint, Masters, <hi>Andrew Ramsay, Alex. Hender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, Robert Dowglas, William Colvill, William Bennet</hi> Ministers at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> M. <hi>William Arthur</hi> Minister at S. <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> M. <hi>James Robertson, John Logan, Robert Lighton,</hi> Commissioners from <hi>Dalkeith</hi> to this Assembly: Masters, <hi>Andrew Blackhall, James Fleeming, Robert Ker,</hi> Commissioners from <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingtoun</hi> to this Assembly: Masters, <hi>George Hamilton, Robert Blair, Arthur Mortoun, David Dalgleish, Andrew Bennet, Walter Greg, John Moncreff, John Smith, George Gillespie, John Row, John Duncan, Walter Bruce,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners for the Presbyteries within the Province of <hi>Fyffe:</hi> M. <hi>David Calderwood</hi> Minister at <hi>Pencaitland,</hi> M. <hi>John Adamson</hi> Principal of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> M. <hi>John Strang</hi> Principal of the Colledge of <hi>Glasgow,</hi> M. <hi>David Dickson,</hi> M. <hi>James Bonar,</hi> M. <hi>Robert Bailie,</hi> M. <hi>John Bell,</hi> M. <hi>Robert Ramsay,</hi> M. <hi>George Young,</hi> M. <hi>Henry Guthrie,</hi> M. <hi>Samuel Oustein,</hi> M. <hi>John Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertson</hi> Minister at S. <hi>Johnstoun,</hi> M. <hi>John Robertson</hi> Minister at <hi>Dundie,</hi> M. <hi>John Hume</hi> Minister at <hi>Eckills,</hi> M. <hi>Andrew Cant,</hi> M. <hi>William Guild,</hi> M. <hi>Samuel Rutherfurd,</hi> M. <hi>James Martin,</hi> M. <hi>Alexander Monroe,</hi> M. <hi>Robert Murray,</hi> M. <hi>John Maclellan, Andrew Doncanson,</hi> M. <hi>Silvester Lambie,</hi> M. <hi>Gilbert Ross,</hi> Ministers: Marquesse of <hi>Argyle,</hi> Earles of <hi>Lauderdaile, Glencarne, Kinghorne, Eglintoun, Weemes, Cassils:</hi> Lords, <hi>Gordoun, Maitland, Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carras,</hi> Sir <hi>Patrick Hepburne</hi> of <hi>Wauchtoun,</hi> Sir <hi>David Home</hi> of <hi>Wedderburne,</hi> Sir <hi>David Creightoun</hi> of <hi>Lugtoun,</hi> Sir <hi>David Barclay</hi> of <hi>Cullearnie, John Henderson</hi> of <hi>Fordell.</hi> M. <hi>George Winrame</hi> of <hi>Libertoun,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Drummond,</hi> Sir <hi>William Carmichaell, John Binnie, Thomas Paterson, John Sempill, John Kennedy</hi> of <hi>Air, John Leslie</hi> from <hi>Aberdene, William Glendining</hi> Provest of <hi>Kirkubright, John Colzear,</hi> Ruling Elders, with the concurse of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curator of the Kirk: And grants to them full Power and Commission in this <hi>interim,</hi> betwixt and the next Assembly, for to meet and conveen at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> upon the 17. day of this moneth of <hi>August,</hi> and upon any other day, or in any other place, as they shall think convenient: And being met and conveened, or any fifteen of them, there being alwayes twelve Ministers present: With full power for to consider and performe what they finde necessary for the Ministerie, by preaching, supplicating, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of draughts of one Confession, one Catechisme, one directory of publike Worship (which are alwayes to be revised by the next Generall Assembly) and by all other lawfull &amp; Ecclesiastick wayes, for furtherance of this great Work in the Union of this Iland in Religion and Kirk-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and for continuance of our own peace at home, and of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon peace betwixt the Nations, and keeping of good correspondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Kirks of this Iland. Like as if it shall please God to blesse the prayers and endeavours of his Saints for this blessed Union, and that if either the Lords of Councell, or Commissioners for the Peace shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire their concurse at home or abroad, by sending Commissioners with theirs to His Majesty and Parliament for that effect, or that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves shall finde it necessary; The Assembly grants full power to them, not only to concurre by all lawfull and Ecclesiastick wayes, with the Councell
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:205458:29"/>and Conservators of the Peace at home, but also to send some to present and prosecute their desires and humble advice to His Majesty and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and the Ministerie there, for the furthering and perfecting o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> so good and great a Worke. Like as, with power to them to promove their other desires, overtures and recommendations of this Assembly, to the Kings Majestie, Lords of Councell, Session, Exchequer, and Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Parliament, for plantation of Kirks, for common burdens, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of the common peace, and to the Parliament of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in case it fall out <hi>pro re nata</hi> before the next Assembly. And such like, with as full power to them to proceed, treat and determine in any other matters to be committed to them by this Assembly, as if the famine were herein particularly insert, and with as ample power to proceede in the matters particularly or generally above-mentioned, as any Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners of Generall Assemblies have had, and have been in use of before: They being alwayes comptable to, and censurable by the next Generall Assembly, for their proceedings thereanent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>Sess. XIII. 6. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642. A Petition from some distressed Professors in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">To the reverend and right Honourable the Moderator and remanent members of the Generall Assembly of <hi>Scotland,</hi> conveened at <hi>S. Andrews,</hi> July <hi>1642.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The humble Petition of the most part of the Scottish Nation in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in their own names, and in name of the rest of the Protestants there.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>Humbly sheweth,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat where your Petitioners, by the great blessing of the Lord, enjoyed for a little while a peaceable and fruitfull Ministerie of the Gospel, yet through our own abuse of so rich a mercy, and through the tyrannie of the Prelates, we have been a long time spoiled of our Ministers (a yoke to many of us heavier then death) who being chased into <hi>Scotland,</hi> were not altogether un-usefull in the day of your need; And we having been since oppressed and scattered; as sheep who have no shepherd, now at last the wise and righteous hand of the Lord, by the sword of the Rebels, hath bereft us of our friends, and spoiled us of our goods, and left us but a few, and that a poor handfull of many, and hath chased from us the rest that were called our Ministers; the greatest part whereof we could scarce esteem such, as being rather Officers to put the Prelats Injunctions in execution, then feeders of our souls: So that now being visited with sword and sicknesse, and under some apprehension of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, if withall we shall taste of the sorest of all plagues, to be altogether deprived of the Ministery of the Word, we shall become in so much a worse condition then any Pagans, as that once we enjoyed a better: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:205458:29"/>know we what hand to turn us to for help, but to the Land so far ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged by the Lords late rare mercies, and so far enriched to furnish help of that kinde; a Land whence many of us drew our blood and breath, and where (pardon the necessary boldnesse) some of our own Ministers now are, who were so violently plucked from us, so sore against both their own and our wills; yea, the Land that so tenderly in their bosoms received our poor out-casts, and that hath already sent us so rich a supply of able and prosperous Souldiers to revenge our wrong.</p>
               <p>Therefore, although we know that your zeale and brotherly affection would urge you to take notice without our advertisement, yet give us leave in the bowels of our Lord Jesus Christ, to intreat, if there be any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any fellowship of the spirit, if any bowels of mercy, that now in this nick of time, when the sword of the Enemie making way for a more profitable entertaining the Gospel, having also banished the Prelates, and their followers, when our extremity of distresse, and the fair hopes of speedy settling of peace, hath opened so fair a doore to the Gospel, you would take the cause of your younger sister, that hath no brests, to your serious consideration, and pity poore <hi>Macedonians</hi> crying to you that ye would come over and help us, being the servants of the God of your Fathers, and claiming interest with you in a common Covenant, that according to the good hand of God upon us, ye may send us Ministers for the house of our God. We do not take upon us to prescribe to you the way or the number, but in the view of all, the finger of the Lord points at these, whom though persecution of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats drew from us, yet our interest in them could not be taken away, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we trust in regard of several of them, called home by death, your bounty will super-adde some able men of your own that may help to lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Gods house, according to the Pattern. But for these so unjustly reft from us, not only our necessity, but equity pleads, that either you would send them all over, which were a Work to be parallelled to the glories of the Primitive times, or at least that ye would declare them tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sportable, that when Invitators shall be sent to any of them, wherein they may discerne a call from God, there may be no difficultie in their loosing from thence, but they may come back to perfect what they began, and may get praise and fame in the Land, where they were put to shame. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are you to question your power over us so to doe, or crave a president of your own practise in that kind, for our extraordinary need calling on you, furnisheth you with a power to make this a president for the like cases hereafter: herein if you shall lay aside the particular concernment of some few places, which you may easily out of your rich Nurseries plant again, and make use of your publike spirits, which are not spent, but increases by your so many noble designes; you shall leave upon us and our posteritie the stamp of an obligation that cannot be delete, or that cannot be expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; you shall send to all the neighbouring Churches a pattern, and erect for after-ages a monument of self-denying tender reale; you shall disburden the Land of the many out-casts, who will follow over their Ministers; and you shall make it appear, that the churlish bounty of the Prelats, which at first cast some of these men over to us, is not comparable with the cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:205458:30"/>liberalitie of a rightly constitute Generall Assembly, to whom we are perswaded, the Lord will give seed for the loane which you bestow on the Lord; yea, the day may come, when a Generall Assembly in this Land may returne to you the first fruits of thanks, for the plants of your free gift. And although you were scant of furniture of this kinde your selves, or might apprehend more need then formerly, yet doubtlesse, your bowels of compassion would make your deep povertie even in a great tryal of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, abound to the riches of your liberalitie. But now seeing you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in all things, and have formerly given so ample a proof of your large bestowing on Churches abroad in <hi>Germanie</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> knowing that you are not wearied in well-doing, we confidently promise to our selves in your name, that ye will abound in this grace also, following the example of our Lord and the Primitive Churches, who alwayes sent out disciples in paires. But if herein our hopes shall faile us, we shall not know whether to wish that we had died with our Brethren by the Enemies hand; for we shall be as if it were said unto us, <hi>Goe serve other Gods;</hi> yet looking for another kinde of Answer at your hands, for in this you are to us as an Angel of God, we have sent these bearers, M. <hi>John Gordoun</hi> and M. <hi>Hugh Campbell</hi> our Brethren, who may more particularly informe you of our case, and desire that at their returne, they may refresh the bowels of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your most instant and earnest Supplicants.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Commission to some Ministers to go to <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly having received a Petition subscribed by a consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> intimating their deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition, through want of the Ministerie of the Gospel, occasioned by the tyrannie of the Prelats, and the sword of the Rebels, and desiring some Ministers, especially such as had been cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed from them, by the persecution of the Prelats, and some others to be added, either to be sent presently over to reside amongst them, or declared transportable, that upon invitation from them, they might goe and settle there; together with some particular Petitions, desiring the returne of some particular Ministers, who had laboured there before: All which the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly hath taken to their serious consideration, being most heartily wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to sympathize with every member of Christs Body, although never so remote; much more with that Plantation there, which for the most part was a Branch of the Lords Vine, planted in this Land. In which sollicitude, as they would be loath to usurpe without their own bounds, or stretch themselves beyond their own measure; so they dare not be wanting, to the enlargement of Christs Kingdome, where so loud a cry of so extreame necessitie, could not but stirre up the bowels of Christian compassion. And although they conceive, that the present unsettled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition both of Church, and State, and Land, will not suffer them as yet to loose any to make constant abode there; yet they have resolved to send over some for the present exigent till the next Generall Assembly, by courses to stay there four moneths allanerly: And therefore doe hereby
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:205458:30"/>authorize and give Commission to the persons following, to wit, M. <hi>Robert Blair,</hi> Minister at S. <hi>Andrews,</hi> and M. <hi>James Hamilton,</hi> Minister at <hi>Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freis</hi> for the first four moneths: M. <hi>Robert Ramsay,</hi> Minister at <hi>Glasgow,</hi> and M. <hi>John Maclelland</hi> Minister at <hi>Kirkudbright,</hi> for the next four moneths: and to M. <hi>Robert Baillie,</hi> professor of divinitie in the Universitie of <hi>Glasgow,</hi> and M. <hi>John Levistoun,</hi> Minister of <hi>Stranraire</hi> for the last four moneths: To repair into the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and there to visit, comfort, instruct and encourage the scattered flocks of Christ, to employ to their uttermost with all faithfulnesse and singlenesse of heart, in planting and watering, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the direction of Jesus Christ, and according to the doctrine and discipline of this Church in all things, And if need be (with concurrence of such of the Ministers of the Army as are there) to try and ordain such as shall be found qualified for the Ministerie, Giving charge unto the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons foresaid in the sight of God, that in doctrine, in worship, in discipline, and in their dayly conversation, they studie to approve themselves as the Ministers of Jesus Christ, and that they be comptable to the Generall As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of this Kirk, in all things. And in case if any of the above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Ministers be impeded by sicknesse, or otherwise necessarily detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from this service, the Assembly ordaines the Commissioners residing at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> for the publike affairs of the Church, to nominate in their place well qualified men, who hereby are authorized to undertake the foresaid imployment, as if they had been expressely nominate in the face of the Assembly. And this, although possibly it shall not fully satisfie the large expectation of the Brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet the Assembly is confident they will take in good part at this time, that which is judged most conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for their present condition, even a lent mite out of their own, not very great plenty, to supply the present necessity; requiring of them no other recompence, but that they in all cheerefulnesse may embrace and make use of the message of salvation, and promising to enlarge their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted bounty at the next Assembly, as they shall finde the Worke of the Lord there to require. In the meane while, wishing that these who are sent, may come with the full blessing of the Gospel and peace, and recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, their labours, and these to whom they are sent, to the rich blessing of the great shepherd of the flock.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Sess. XIII. 6. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642. <hi>Act against slandering of Ministers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall Assembly considering the malice of divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in raising calumnies and scandalls against Ministers, which is not onely injurious to their persons, and discredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the holy calling of the Ministerie, but doth also prove often a great prejudice and hinderance to the promoving of the Gospel: Doe therefore ordain Presbyteries and Synods to proceed diligently in processe against all persons, that shall reproach or scandall Ministers, with the censures of the Kirk, even to the highest, according as they shall finde the degree or quality of the scandal deserve.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:205458:31"/>
               <head>Act anent ordering of the Assembly House.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Assembly for better order in time coming ordains the Act of the Assembly at <hi>Aberdene</hi> for ordering the House of the Assembly to be kept hereafter punctually. And for that effect, that the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine be reade the first Session of every Assembly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act for remembring in publike Prayers the desires of the Assembly to the King and Parliament, and indiction of a publike Fast.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Generall Assembly being desirous to promove the great work of Unity in Religion, and Uniformity in Church-government, in all thir three Dominions, for which the Assembly hath humbly supplicate the Kings Majestie, and remonstrate their desires to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> lest they should be wanting in any meane that may further so glorious and so good a Work: Doe ordain, that not only the said Declaration to the Parliament, and supplication to the Kings Majestie, shall be accompanied with the earnest Petitions and prayers of the whole Brethren in private and publike, for the Lords blessing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, according to the laudable custome of our predecessors, who in the year of God 1589. ordaines that the Brethren in their private and publike prayers, recommend unto God the estate of the afflicted Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> But having just cause of fear, that the iniquities of the Land, which so much abound, may marre this so great a Work, doe also ordain a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Fast to be kept on the second Lords day of <hi>September,</hi> and the Wednesday following throughout the whole Kingdome for the causes after specified.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Grosse ignorance and all sort of wickednesse among the greater part, security, meer formality and unfruitfulnesse among the best, and unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse in all.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The sword raging throughout all Christendome, but most barbarously in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and dayly more and more threatned in <hi>England,</hi> through the lamentable division betwixt the King and the Parliament there, tending to the subversion of Religion and Peace in all the three Kingdomes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> That God may graciously blesse the supplication of the Assembly to the Kings Majesty, and their motion to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> for Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in Religion, and Uniformity of Kirk-government, and all other meanes which may serve for the promoving of so great a Worke, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Kingdome of Christ every where.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> That God may powerfully overturne all wicked plots and designes of Antichrist and his followers, and all divisive motions against the course of Reformation, and the so much longed for Union of the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> That God may blesse the harvest. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="reference">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:205458:31"/>
               <head>Reference from the Presbyterie of <hi>Kirkcaldie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nent the Acts of Assemblies, for observation of the Lords Day, profaned by going of Salt-pannes, That this Assembly would declare the limits of the Sabbath, during which the Pannes should stand.</p>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe Assembly referres the Answer of this Question, to the Acts of former Assemblies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <div type="reference">
               <head>Reference from the Synode of <hi>Fyffe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Provincial of <hi>Angus</hi> keep their meeting on the same day with the Synod of <hi>Fyffe,</hi> which breakes the correspondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, appointed by the Generall Assembly of <hi>Glasgow.</hi>
               </p>
               <argument>
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe Assembly ordaines the Provinciall Assembly of</hi> Angus <hi>to keep their first meeting upon the third Tuesday of</hi> April, <hi>conforme to the Act of the said Assembly of</hi> Glasgow.</p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <div type="overtures">
               <head>Overtures to be advised by Presbyteries against the next Assembly.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow Appeals shall be brought in to the Generall Assemblies, and by what sort of citation.</p>
               <p>What shall be the prescription of scandalls, within what space of time shall they be challenged, whether after three years, the Minister having been allowed and approved in life and doctrine by Synods, Presbyteries, and Visitations.</p>
               <p>What order shall be taken for keeping Generall Assemblies, when Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries send not the full number of Commissioners: Or when the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners abide not untill the conclusion and dissolving of the Assembly.</p>
               <p>Order to be advised for Testimonialls.</p>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe Assembly appoints the next Generall Assembly to hold at</hi> Edinburgh <hi>the first Wednesday of</hi> August, 1643.</p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:205458:32"/>
            <head>INDEX OF THE PRINCIPALL Acts of the Generall Assemblies holden at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 1639. At <hi>Aberdene</hi> 1640. At <hi>S. Andrews</hi> and <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 1641. And at <hi>S. Andrews</hi> 1642. which are not Printed.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Index of the principall Acts of the Assembly at <hi>Edinburgh 1639.</hi> not Printed.</head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kings Majesties Commission to <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of <hi>Traquair.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Election of M. <hi>David Dickson</hi> Moderator.</item>
               <item>The Kings Majesties Commissioners, and the Assemblies Declarations anent the Assembly of <hi>Glasgow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Renunciation of M. <hi>Alex. Lindsey</hi> pretended Bishop of <hi>Dunkell,</hi> of Episcopacie.</item>
               <item>Commission for visitation of the Universitie of <hi>S. Andrews.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commission for visitation of the Universitie of <hi>Glasgow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act reviving former Acts against going of Salt-pans on the Sabbath day.</item>
               <item>Act for drawing up of a Catechisme.</item>
               <item>Articles and Overtures to be presented to the ensuing Parliament.</item>
               <item>The report of the Committee appointed for examination of the Book called, <hi>The Kings Manifesto,</hi> or, <hi>Declaration.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Covenant or confession of Faith.</item>
               <item>Act anent the adjoyning of some Kirks in the Ile of <hi>Boot</hi> to the Presb. of <hi>Denune.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act adjoyning some Kirks in the Iles of <hi>Coill</hi> and <hi>Tyrie,</hi> to the Provinciall of <hi>Kilmoire.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commis. for visitation of the Colledge of <hi>Aberdene.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commis. to the Presbytery of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Index of the principall Acts of the Assembly at <hi>Aberdene 1640.</hi> not Printed.</head>
               <item>ELection of M. <hi>Andr. Ramsay</hi> Moderator.</item>
               <item>Act against profaning of the Sabbath.</item>
               <item>Act anent Charmers.</item>
               <item>Act renewing a former Act made against Priors and Abbots.</item>
               <item>Commission for attending the Parliament.</item>
               <item>Commission anent the Province of <hi>Rosse.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commis. anent the Presbytery of <hi>Kirkwall.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act anent the Presbytery-seat of <hi>Selkirk.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Report of the Visitors of the Universitie of <hi>Glasgow,</hi> and a new Commission of visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of that University.</item>
               <item>Act anent the carriage of Ministers.</item>
               <item>Act anent the ordering of Family Exercise.</item>
               <item>Act for Ruling Elders keeping of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries.</item>
               <item>Act anent Magistrates being Members of Kirk Session.</item>
               <item>Approbation of the proceedings of the Commissioners appointed to attend the preceding Parliament.</item>
               <item>Act anent abolishing idolatrous monuments</item>
               <item>Act anent abolishing idolatrous monuments in and about <hi>Aberdene.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The report of the Visitors of the Universitie of <hi>Aberdene.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commission for visiting the Universitie of <hi>Aberdene.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Index of the principall Acts of the Assembly holden at S. <hi>Andrews</hi> and <hi>Edinburgh 1641.</hi> not Printed.</head>
               <item>HIs Majesties Commission to <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of <hi>Weemes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter from the Parliament to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Assembly.</item>
               <item>Act anent the continuation of M. <hi>Andrew Ramsay</hi> Moderator.</item>
               <item>His Majesties Letter to the Assembly.</item>
               <item>Act anent the translation of the Assembly from S. <hi>Andrews</hi> to <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Election of M. <hi>Alex. Henderson</hi> Moderator.</item>
               <item>Declaration of the Assemb. anent the transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof to <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act for drawing up one Catechisme, one Confession of Faith, Directory of publike worship and form of Kirk-government.</item>
               <item>Act anent M. <hi>Andrew Ramsays</hi> delivery to the Clerk the Books, <hi>Warnesius</hi> Book, and others, which he received at <hi>Aberdene.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Overtures anent transportation of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and plantation of Schooles, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended
<pb facs="tcp:205458:32"/>to be advised by Synods.</item>
               <item>Ref. to the Parl. anent the Kirks of <hi>Dunkeld.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act anent M. <hi>David Calderwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commis. anent erecting a Presb. in <hi>Biggar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Com. for visitation of <hi>Orknay</hi> and <hi>Zetland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act anent bringing of the Synode Books to the Assemblies.</item>
               <item>Ref. from the Parl. anent a Band and a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per called a <hi>Manifesto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act anent the deleting of the E. of <hi>Traquairs</hi> Declaration out of the Books of secret Councell.</item>
               <item>Report of Overtures made anent the planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Kirks in the <hi>High-lands.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commission for visitation of the Universitie of <hi>S. Andrews.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commis. for visitation of the Universitie of <hi>Glasgow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commis. to attend the Parliament.</item>
               <item>Ref. to that Commis. anent the Presb. of <hi>Sky.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Index of the principall Acts of the Assembly holden at <hi>S. Andrews 27.</hi> July <hi>1642.</hi> not Printed.</head>
               <item>HIs Majesties Commission granted to <hi>Charles</hi> Earle of <hi>Dumfermling.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Election of M. <hi>Robert Douglas</hi> Moderator.</item>
               <item>Acceptation of the Commission from the Scottish Kirk at <hi>Campheir,</hi> granted to M. <hi>William Spang.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act renewing the Commissions for visitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Universities of S. <hi>Andrews</hi> and <hi>Glasgow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act anent delivery of the Irish contribution to the receivers appointed by the secret Councell.</item>
               <item>Act anent idolatrous monuments in <hi>Ruth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act anent the Books of the Presbyteries in our Armie that went to <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act anent planting the Kirk of <hi>Kilwinning.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commis. anent erecting a Presb. in <hi>Biggar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act repealing the act of the Synod of <hi>Gallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> concerning tryal of actuall Ministers.</item>
               <item>The Kings Declar. anent the gift of 500 l.</item>
               <item>Act for sending of Expectants to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and for a Commission to be drawn up to some Ministers to go there.</item>
               <item>Recom. to the Marques of <hi>Argyle</hi> anent <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick Egertie</hi> Priest, and all other Priests, or sayers of Masse in the North Iles, or within the bounds of his Justiciarie.</item>
               <item>Act anent the reponing of M. <hi>Gilbert Power.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act for putting the Overtures anent main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Bursars in every Presb. in practise.</item>
               <item>Report of the Com. for revising some Synod Books, and the Assemblies approbation.</item>
               <item>Act for giving transumpts of the Covenant and Band.</item>
               <item>Act for sending of Generall acts of Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies to Synods.</item>
               <item>Act anent <hi>Iames Murray.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Report of the Committee of reports of the proceedings of the Commissioners of the last Assembly appointed to attend the Parl. with certain Overtures of the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies approbation thereof, with the double of the Signator of 500 l. sent to His Majestie.</item>
               <item>Com. for visitation of <hi>Orknay</hi> and <hi>Zetland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ref. to the Commis. of this Assembly, anent the choise of any Minister to go to <hi>Ireland</hi> in place of any of the 6. appointed by this Assem. to that effect, in case they or any of them be impeded by sicknesse or death.</item>
               <item>Recom. of the <hi>Iles, Anandail, Escdaill, Lid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disdaill, &amp;c.</hi> for want of Kirks &amp; Schools of the Presbyteries of <hi>Lochmaben,</hi> and <hi>Newbie,</hi> for want of a civill Mastistrate, to the Commission for planting of Kirks, and secret Councell, <hi>respective.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ref. to the Commission of this Assembly for planting of the Kirk of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act anent M. <hi>Colvils</hi> invitation to S. <hi>Andrews</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commission anent the planting of the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Kirk of S. <hi>Andrews.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>References and Overtures, and the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies answer thereto.</item>
               <item>Ref. to the Commis. of this Assembly anent M. <hi>Iames Fairlie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ref. to the Commis. of this Assembly anent the planting of the Kirk of <hi>Dundie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Overtures anent the Kirk of <hi>Campheir.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Recom. to the Magistrates of <hi>Glasgow</hi> anent Mundayes Market.</item>
               <item>Act anent giving in to the Clerk the List of Expectants.</item>
               <item>Act giving power and liberty to Sir <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald Iohnstoun</hi> Procurator for the Kirk, and Clerk to the Generall Assembly, to adjoyn any to himself, or to depute any in these Offices whom he shall think fit.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>